<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Shauna Gordon]]></title>
  <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-31T02:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shauna Gordon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways To Keep Going (When You're Going Through Hell)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/10/30/motivation/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T22:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/10/30/motivation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When in the throes of a depressive episode (or on the edge of an anxiety attack or any other such motivation killer), it can be hard to maintain motivation and productivity. This can be detrimental when other people rely on you, or when you have a job to hold down.</p>

<p>Over the years, I&rsquo;ve found a number of things that have helped keep me motivated through low times, and have decided to share them. Unlike other articles giving advice on &ldquo;cheering up,&rdquo; the items here may or may not actually lift your mood. That&rsquo;s not the point of them, and anyone who&rsquo;s dealt with depression will tell you that most of the time, things designed to &ldquo;cheer you up&rdquo; don&rsquo;t really work. If it does lift your mood, then that&rsquo;s a positive side effect, but as Winston Churchill put it, &ldquo;when you&rsquo;re going through hell, keep going.&rdquo; These items are intended to do <em>that</em> &mdash; help you keep going.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Eat&hellip;</h2>

<p>Dysfunctional mental states, be it depression or mania, tend to screw with our eating patterns. It&rsquo;s important during these times more than ever to make sure we keep good habits.</p>

<h3>&hellip;The Right Amount</h3>

<p>Depression, especially, does one of two things to the appetite. It either kills it, or makes the person want to eat everything. For various other reasons, other mental illnesses often have similar effects. Both of these things have their own problems.</p>

<p>Eating too much food, especially the usual comfort foods of sugars and refined carbohydrates, is bad for the obvious reason that it will likely lead to weight gain, especially if it happens on a regular basis. Weight gain itself is often a self-esteem killer, and can result in a negative feedback loop, which most people already know.</p>

<p>However, the obvious &ldquo;too much food, not enough movement&rdquo; aside, dysfunctional eating can have more short-term effects on your mood and motivation, especially if you swing the other way and don&rsquo;t eat enough. By not eating enough, you deprive your body of the energy it needs to keep you going. This can start slowing you down as your body tries to conserve energy for vital uses. This state of lethargy can bring the mood down, as well as keep you from being motivated to do things. Again, a feedback loop ensues.</p>

<h3>&hellip;At Regular Intervals</h3>

<p>Like making sure to eat enough, eating at regular intervals is also important, I&rsquo;ve found. I&rsquo;m not a fan of the whole &ldquo;eat six small meals&rdquo; thing, but going half a day without food? Not necessarily a good idea. Even if you don&rsquo;t feel terribly hungry, it&rsquo;s a good idea to eat at least a little bit of food, or eat once you get hungry, even if it&rsquo;s starting to get close to the next meal time. I&rsquo;ve personally found that both my motivation and my mood start going down the farther apart my meals are. So, try to keep your regular eating schedule.</p>

<h3>&hellip;Wholesome, Whole Foods&hellip;</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found that my overall mood and motivation have largely stabilized (and at a higher base level) since switching to a whole foods-based diet. The better I eat, the less of a rollercoaster I have going on in my head.</p>

<p>A lot of the diseases of civilization can be traced back to malnourishment, at least in part. Yeah, we have no shortage of food in our Western society, but look at the quality of the vast majority of it. Frankly, it sucks, and is largely devoid of nutrients. Get back to the basics &mdash; meat, fruits, vegetables, etc. &mdash; and odds are very good that you&rsquo;ll start to see major improvements in all areas of your physical health, as your vitamin stores start actually filling back up. <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2738337/">Deficiencies in things like folate, B-12, and magnesium</a> can do a number on the brain and exacerbate depression, schizophrenia, and anxiety, among others. Eating whole foods provides your body with the most bioavailable forms of these nutrients.</p>

<h4>&hellip;Including Healthy Fats</h4>

<p>I am a big fan of the low carb, high fat (LCHF) way of eating. The ketogenic diet (an &ldquo;extreme&rdquo; form of LCHF, where fat intake is upwards of 80-90% of total calories) was originally created for epilepsy, but has <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3321471/">since been studied (or slated for study) for other neurological issues, including such things as depression, migraines, and more.</a> I had switched to it for other reasons, but found positive effects in this area, as well.</p>

<p>One of the big things that a LCHF diet teaches you is that the conventional wisdom that has been burned into our brains is wrong (which is now starting to come back to mainstream media). Where conventional wisdom lauds polyunsaturated fats and vilifies saturated fats, LCHF shows how important naturally occurring saturated fats really are, and that polyunsaturated fats should be consumed only in moderation (and certainly not in the heavily-refined, Omega-6-heavy oils that conventional wisdom have on a pedestal). So, when I say &ldquo;include healthy fats,&rdquo; I also mean saturated fats, as well as monounsaturated fats, and, more sparingly, polyunsaturated fats. The only fat to really avoid is trans fat.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to switch to a LCHF diet to benefit from including good fats, but a good grass-fed butter and some virgin coconut oil are manna from the gods, let me tell you.</p>

<p>(I&rsquo;m not going to go into all the nitty-gritty details of the research regarding fat in this post, or even on this blog. I have a more health/fitness/diet related blog and will write about it in the future. When that happens, I&rsquo;ll link to it for the research details. In the meantime, I welcome you to check out the recent <a href="http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleid=1846638&amp;resultClick=3">meta-analysis of a few dozen studies regarding saturated fats and heart disease</a>, and <a href="http://vimeo.com/45485034">Dr. Peter Attia&rsquo;s talk on the history of the anti-fat conventional wisdom</a>.)</p>

<h2>Do An Intense Workout At Least Once A Week</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s just something about doing something so intense that you can&rsquo;t help but focus on it and be in the moment, and, after you&rsquo;re done, want little more than a hot shower and comfy bed, that helps relieve the latent, low-level anxiety and stress that seems to kill productivity. I&rsquo;ve found that I&rsquo;m a giant ball of nerves by Wednesday afternoon, but after my evening boxing class, it&rsquo;s like night and day, and that carries me through the remainder of the week.</p>

<p>The important thing for this is to find something that forces you to focus on the moment, and wear you out. Things like martial arts or cardio boxing/kickboxing are good options, because you have to concentrate on your form, posture, moves, etc. Some martial arts also teach you various meditation/focusing techniques that can carry over to the rest of your life. It doesn&rsquo;t have to be these things, though. If you enjoy running, for example, then do sprints, or check out Parkour. What matters is forcing you into the moment and, to a lesser extent, getting the endorphine rush that comes with a strenuous workout.</p>

<h2>Get Outside And Go For A Walk</h2>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t so much about fitness (the walk), but more about getting outside. Most people, and especially those with depression, are deficient in Vitamin D. <em>The</em> best way to get Vitamin D is from spending some time out in the sun, without sunscreen (Vitamin D synthesis is triggered by UV exposure, which is blocked by sunscreen). The walk is an added bonus to get the blood flowing, loosen stiff joints, and help build and maintain a base level of fitness, and just getting away from the computer helps your mind take a break and subconsciously mull over that problem you&rsquo;ve been dealing with all morning. I personally enjoy tossing on a Podcast and walking for about an hour at an easy pace (shout out to Shawn McCool and his Laravel.io podcast, which are pretty consistently about an hour). If you want a virtual walking buddy, feel free to <a href="http://runkeeper.com/user/gordondev">hit me up on RunKeeper</a> (great app to track your routes and distances, by the way).</p>

<h2>Take A Spa Day Once In A While</h2>

<p>Seriously, it seems really girly to have a spa day once in a while, but it&rsquo;s astounding how good it can be at relaxing you (and there are places that will give men massages and facials, too). Like the intense workout, it helps prompt you to be in the moment, and it feels extraordinarily good to get a nice massage (I&rsquo;m a fan of deep tissue massages, myself) and release that pent up tension in your shoulders and back.</p>

<p>If you <em>really</em> don&rsquo;t like the idea of a spa day (or can&rsquo;t afford it), do something similarly relaxing, even if it&rsquo;s just a hot bath or meditation. Being able to physically relax your body for a time can help relieve low-level psychological stress, which can, in turn, increase your motivation to get things done. Some type of &ldquo;me&rdquo; day also gives you something to look forward to, if you need something to get you through the day.</p>

<h2>Create A Todo List</h2>

<p>It feels good to me to check off an item on a list. At the very least, though, I&rsquo;ve found it helps get that list out of my head and off-load it from my memory, so that I can use those cognitive resources for <em>actually getting that shit done.</em> This has proven to be a <em>huge</em> benefit to my productivity &mdash; particularly for my side projects &mdash; as I find myself glancing at the list and going &ldquo;I want to work on that tonight.&rdquo; Even if I don&rsquo;t finish the task in question, I don&rsquo;t have to worry about keeping it on my mental list, because it&rsquo;s on a physical/digital one. It actually allows me to juggle the few dozen ideas and side projects I have bouncing around my head, without feeling overwhelmed by them (which is good, because they&rsquo;re all freakin&#8217; time-consuming as hell, and I can&rsquo;t generally just knock two or three out in an evening).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become a fan of <a href="http://www.any.do/">Any.do</a>, because I can set recurrances (like doing Yoga each day), or set some tasks to &ldquo;Someday,&rdquo; which keeps them separate from the stuff to do &ldquo;Today.&rdquo; I also love the integration it has with my Android phone, including a calendar app (it&rsquo;s got a slick interface).</p>

<p>I also enjoy <a href="https://workflowy.com/">Workflowy</a>, and used it for a short time as a Todo list, as well. It&rsquo;s become more of a shopping list for me when I do use it, but I know a few people who prefer it over other things for any kind of list making. There are many others to choose from, too, so it doesn&rsquo;t really matter <em>what</em> tool you use, as long as it works for you.</p>

<h2>Keep A Clean Working Area</h2>

<p>Clutter is often a trigger for stress. It can add cognitive overhead and lower your stress tolerance or threshold for getting overwhelmed. So, while it may not seem like it&rsquo;s adding stress or exacerbating depression symptoms, it might still be affecting you. Keep your work area (and, ideally, any area you spend a fair amount of time in) clutter free. In practice, this works best if you keep it clean, instead of trying to clean it while in a low state (though if it&rsquo;s mild enough, or if the clutter is light enough, cleaning it up might serve as a motivation booster).</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>Hopefully, one or more of these suggestions will help. I&rsquo;ve found, too, that a lot of these work best when you make a habit out of them. A single walk is pretty good, by itself, but making it a daily (or nearly so) habit helps keep your body increase its energy levels over time, giving you a higher base level of energy, which makes getting things done just a little bit easier. So, give one or two (or three) a shot for a couple of weeks and see how they work for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Open Letter To Recruiters]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/10/15/dear-recruiters/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T23:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/10/15/dear-recruiters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Third Party Recruiters,</p>

<p>Due to the high volume of contact requests I’ve received, I have decided to write this open letter in order to improve the quality of my network.</p>

<p>The Greater Columbus Area is home to a very large number of third party recruiting companies. This means <strong>you have a lot of competition</strong>. Competition should mean improved quality. Unfortunately, what I generally see is rather disappointing.</p>

<p>We tech folks are generally a merit-based people. We’ll respect you if we have reason to do so. You can earn that respect by demonstrating that you respect us and what we do (and no, saying that you do doesn’t cut it; show, don’t tell). Here are some ways to do that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Have some fundamental understanding of the technology</h2>

<p>Or, <em>don&rsquo;t play buzzword Bingo.</em></p>

<p>I don’t expect you to have been a developer, but I do expect basic, high-level knowledge, such as the fact that <strong>Java and JavaScript are two very different things.</strong> How can you expect to get proper, let alone quality, matches for the companies you’re recruiting for if you can’t even get the technology right?</p>

<h2>Pay attention to the last time I used a technology, and the ones I use now</h2>

<p>Or, <em>do some some homework.</em></p>

<p>I know there’s a certain amount of crossover when it comes to technologies, but there’s also a sort of expiration date, especially at the Senior Developer level. <strong>I have not touched Java since 2007.</strong> Odds are, I am <em>not</em> a good fit for that great Android developer position you’re looking to fill, nor will I be interested in it, nor am I likely to have anyone in my circles that use it. For the record, my network primarily covers the open source languages (PHP, Ruby, Python) and, to a lesser extent, the .Net languages. However, I won’t be forwarding your leads to them if you haven’t taken the time to build some rapport with me.</p>

<h2>Pay attention to <em>all</em> of the technologies I use</h2>

<p>My time at a design agency has resulted in a number of “front end!” development position leads, since a large portion of my job was HTML and CSS. Now, while a front end development position <em>may</em> not get immediately trashed, you will probably find a far better match with me for a <em>full stack</em> position.</p>

<p>I’ll be among the first to admit &mdash; software is a <em>huge</em> industry (really, there isn’t a word in the English language that adequately describes just how mind-boggling huge an industry it is). Front end web development is, on its own, enormous. If a company is looking for a dedicated front-end person, odds are, I don’t know half of what they’re looking for, at least not to the level that would best serve them. Now, while I’d love to learn it and would have no qualms doing so (hell, it’s how I’ve learned most of the technologies I use at this moment), odds are very good that I’m not as great a match for the company as you might think. There’s probably someone out there better suited to that particular position.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong &mdash; if the company doesn’t mind a little more time to pick up the new technology <em>and</em> the ins and outs of the new (to me) company, then by all means. However, most companies, especially those going through the heavy, active recruiting that you get paid to do, generally prefer someone who can “hit the ground running.” Angular/Backbone/Ember/Knockout may be a JavaScript framework, but it’s enough of its own beast that just knowing JavaScript probably isn’t enough for a “hit the ground running” position.</p>

<p>Instead, look at what I <em>do</em> use, and look at <em>all</em> of it, especially in recent gigs. Odds are very good that if you have a position that needs a little bit of everything, then I <em>am</em> a good fit for it. Framework matches? Even better!</p>

<h2>Write better introductions</h2>

<p>I literally received an email from a third party recruiter that started like this:</p>

<blockquote>I was just cruising around the web, and I stumbled upon what you&#8217;ve been up to on the software engineering front.</blockquote>


<p>Seriously? Now, I don’t expect some kind of formal thesis with the formal greetings we all learned in school, but come on. Do you really expect me to believe that you, a person whose entire job is to seek out people like me, was “cruising around the web” and <em>happened</em> to stumble on my website/Twitter/LinkedIn profile? Really, it sounds like a bad pickup line.</p>

<p>Granted, I’m sure there is a certain amount of meandering going on, following leads and connections, friends-of-friends and blog posts by related authors. It’s not like I’ve made myself scarce in the online world. If you really just happened upon my information, then cool, I’ve done my job at least to some extent.</p>

<p>But please don’t fluff it up like the above quote. Something like “I found your LinkedIn profile” or “saw one of your blog posts mentioned in a Tweet on my feed,” or whatever other more straightforward and non-sickening way of telling me where you found my information is much less likely to get your email immediately deleted. You also get some brownie points for being more specific with how you’ve found me.</p>

<h2>For that matter, introduce yourself</h2>

<p>If you send me a LinkedIn invite, and all it reads is the &ldquo;Join my LinkedIn network&rdquo; canned pre-fill text, then your invite will get trashed. I don&rsquo;t collect contacts, especially third party recruiters.</p>

<h2>Be more straightforward in general</h2>

<p>I hate social games. I value straightforwardness and despise things like this:</p>

<blockquote> I came across your profile on LinkedIn while researching Developer professionals. Your background/experience caught my eye so I’m sending you a quick note to see if you&#8217;d be able to point me in the right direction. 
 
Our client is looking for a Web Developer in the Columbus, OH area! Do you know of anyone who may be interested?</blockquote>


<p>Especially when it’s followed by this, when I ask for more information:</p>

<blockquote>I wanted to see if you were still interested in this opportunity! We sat down with the client this week and were able to find out a ton more details of exactly what they are looking for, I would love to talk some details with you!</blockquote>


<p>Now, I understand that, as a third party, you can’t (or are hesitant to) disclose things like the company name (though doing so would earn you some brownie points; otherwise, it conveys the message that you don’t trust me, and that’s not a good start), but if you don’t want your email to end up in the trash bin, then give me at least some information about the job itself &mdash; things like what technologies, number of years experience. You know, the usual.</p>

<p>This also highlights another issue.</p>

<h2>Don’t insist on only talking to me via phone</h2>

<p>First off, if you’re not willing to put something in writing, then that itself raises a red flag and makes me more likely to dismiss you.</p>

<p>Second, phone calls &mdash; particularly unexpected/unsolicited ones &mdash; are intrinsically intrusive. Additionally, developers typically run on what can be described as <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">the maker’s schedule</a>, and I’m not exception. By calling me, you’ve diverted my attention from my work, broken my concentration. <em>The phone call itself does this, even if I don’t answer.</em> At the very least, your call has just cost me <a href="http://blog.ninlabs.com/2013/01/programmer-interrupted/">roughly 10-15 minutes</a> in productivity. Since time is money, you then owe me a fancy coffee at a hipster coffee shop, just for the interruption. If I actually answer and talk to you, you might as well buy me lunch.</p>

<p>In fact, if you’re really interested in <em>me</em> and talking to me, then do that &mdash; buy me lunch. We can organize a lunch meeting via email (when I can respond at a time that suits me), and chat about things then. And keep in mind, it’s not about the free food aspect. It’s about respecting and valuing my time.</p>

<h2>Communicate with your other branches and don’t spam and harass me</h2>

<p>A one point earlier this year, I received <strong>5 emails and 3 phone calls from different people at different branches of the same recruiting company in the span of 2 weeks.</strong> Two weeks! Even worse? Nearly half of those came <em>after I asked them to remove me from their system</em> (for the third time, no less).</p>

<p><em>That</em> will get you reported to the Better Business Bureau, and you <em>will</em> be made known to my network as someone to not work with. Developers talk. Our industry may be huge, but our community is quite small. I can’t tell you the number of people I’ve found that I’ve crossed paths with in one way or another or found that my friends have shared connections beyond casual “friend” or “connection” gathering on social media networks. Earning yourself a place on my blacklist will very likely earn yourself a place on the blacklist of a few dozen other developers (conversely &mdash; earning a place of respect with me will make it more likely to get referrals from me).</p>

<p>I understand that there aren’t really any convenient times during which you can call, but that makes it even <em>more</em> important to not spam or harass me.</p>

<h2>Don’t send me leads in other cities</h2>

<p>Unless I’ve indicated a willingness to relocate (even better, a willingness to relocate to <em>that</em> city), or the company genuinely supports remote working (not just kind of puts up with it), I’m very, very likely not interested in it. Additionally, even if I am interested or would consider it, absence of a relocation package will pretty much guarantee I’ll ignore it. Selling a house and moving a family is a pain in the ass, so there’s a <em>lot</em> of inertia there.</p>

<h1>What I want in a job</h1>

<p>Now that you’ve read this far, let’s look at the things that I want in a job. I’m in a good position right now and am not specifically looking to change. Therefore, while I always keep my ear to the ground, I can afford to be ultra-picky. Odds are very, very good, then, that I will ignore any lead that doesn’t match up with the following things.</p>

<p>These are not the demands of an entitled young worker. These are things that I’ve found work best for me and allow me to be a better employee to an employer. These are also things that I’ve found that say a lot about the quality of the environment. In other words, the more of these qualities that a company fulfills, the more likely I’ll be a good match for the company (not just the position itself).</p>

<h2>Only agencies that truly value their developers</h2>

<p>This really applies to all companies, but from the experiences I’ve had at the ones I worked at suggest that agencies are some of the worst offenders. When the people in an environment that’s proven toxic for me repeatedly tell me that that company is better than the other (big player) agencies that they’ve worked at, that sends a pretty clear message that I want nothing to do with the entire lot.</p>

<p>I’ve worked in agency environments, and they were all a big fail to me. The worst fail was with a company that touted great culture, but it was lip service and superficial things &mdash; the pool table, ping pong table, and video games that I’d seen used a collective less than half a dozen times in the year and a half I was there; the happy hours and parties that were as much a disturbance to us as good things. The things that really matter to good culture &mdash; not overloading us with work, providing us with quiet environments, and the ability of project and account managers to reign in a client and say “no” once in a while (especially when the client expects it without paying extra or adjusting the deadline) &mdash; are what I’m interested in. Without these things, I crash and burn, and such an environment is a toxic one for me.</p>

<h3>Brownie points: encourage self-direction of projects and full project ownership</h3>

<p>I’m a big fan of Zack Holman’s articles on some of GitHub’s ideals. In this case, it’s <a href="http://zachholman.com/posts/how-github-works-creativity/">his “Creativity Means Self-Direction” section of this one</a>. This isn’t a deal-breaking ideal, but the company that does this would be worth its weight in gold, particularly on top of fulfilling the other ideals. I would love to be able to work on the project(s) that I choose to work on, and be able to take full ownership and have a certain amount of control/authority over that project, and tinker it to improve it as I see fit.</p>

<h2>Remote work friendly</h2>

<p>I have found that a company’s view on people working remotely has been a fairly accurate barometer for other environmental mindsets.</p>

<p>My ideal is the option to work full time remotely. <strong>My line of work does not require physical presence in a specific location.</strong> Many of the best teams in my industry are comprised of people who have never met in person. It most certainly can be done successfully, given the right infrastructure.</p>

<p>I may consider a position that allows it on a regular part time basis. <em>This does not mean “you can work from home if you’re snowed in…”</em> but rather, I have the option to, say, work from home on Wednesdays, because those are my most productive days, and I can encourage that productivity by working in an environment that I’ve set up to be ideal for me and don’t have to worry about people walking up to me and interrupting me while I’m in the zone.</p>

<h2>Results-only work environment</h2>

<p>If you don’t know what this is, <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/stories/2006-12-10/smashing-the-clock">here’s some required reading for you</a>, and when you’re done with that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1591842921/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1591842921&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=graywolfweb-20&amp;linkId=PBMFRAJ3BFUSYUQ6">pick up <em>Why Work Sucks And How To Fix It</em> and read it</a> . I’ll wait.</p>

<p>Done with your homework? Good, because this one’s come to be a deal-breaker for me.</p>

<p>In the US, developers are nearly always exempt salary (thank you “Fair” Labor Standards Act…), and most employers are too hung up on number of hours worked. This is <em>a very bad combination,</em> because it is very easily abused to get what amounts to free labor. <a href="http://zachholman.com/posts/how-github-works-hours/">Developers are creative people, with peaks and troughs of productivity.</a> It does a disservice to both us and our employers if we’re not able to honor those troughs by doing something else in our lives that can break us out of these non-productive phases, especially during slow times in the company. Requiring me to work a particular number of hours a day or week, even when there’s no or not much work to do, is not “hour flexibility,” nor is it “work life balance” (especially if I’m required to use accumulated paid time off of any sort if I don’t work those hours). If I’m salaried, you’re paying me for the value I bring to the company, not for my time. If you’re going to hold me to a time clock, pay me proper overtime pay. I’m a professional level employee with an advanced set of skills, not a slave.</p>

<p>In short, <strong>I am much more willing to work overtime when needed if I know that I don’t have to work a “regular” number of hours during the next slow period.</strong></p>

<p>Additionally, a ROWE discourages office politics. I <em>despise</em> office politics and don’t do well with them (for reasons I’ve explained elsewhere on my blog). So, a ROWE is more likely to be a workplace that’s friendlier to my personality, making it that much more likely that my relationship with the company will be a long and happy one.</p>

<h2>Brownie points: use modern tools and technologies</h2>

<p>This isn’t a deal-breaking thing, but it is an ideal. Simply put, I’m able to do more and be more productive when I’m able to work with modern tools, instead of trying to fight with a legacy system that doesn’t follow any standards (unless I’m modernizing said legacy system).</p>

<h1>Phew! You made it!</h1>

<p>Read all the way through that and still have something for me? Awesome! Send it my way, being mindful of the things we talked about here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You're Not Alone]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/08/19/youre-not-alone/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T13:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/08/19/youre-not-alone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been torn over how open I should be with this, particularly in my professional life. My first instinct has been for it to be on a very need to know basis.</p>

<p>Then I met <a href="http://baugues.com/">Greg Baugues</a>.</p>

<p>Greg is a developer evangelist (devangelist) for <a href="http://www.twilio.com/">Twilio</a>, who speaks at conferences about his ADHD and Type II Bipolar, and he gets well-deserved standing ovations pretty much wherever he speaks. I still fight tearing up just thinking about <a href="http://userscape.com/laracon/2014/gregbaugues.html">the talk I attended at Laracon</a>, back in mid-May, where he even took his Bipolar medication on stage.</p>

<p>If you ever have the opportunity, attend this man’s talk. Even if you’ve seen the videos of it.</p>

<p>He’s the driving force behind this entry. Until now, I’ve kept my professional image away from my more personal parts. I’ve compartmentalized my identity, basically. Tech and business here, mental and physical health over there, homesteading over there (insert gestures to different directions here). But the truth is, my having Autism and Depression are part of what shapes me as a person and affects my professional life, whether I want them to or not. And just like I have started looking up to Greg as a role model for someone who has seen success with his ADHD and Bipolar out in the open, the others out there need more people to look up to, as well. We all need people to understand us and our differences, so that they can see us as strengths to be embraced, instead of liabilities to be feared. And, as Robin Williams’ death has shown so vividly, we need to be able to talk about these things openly and not be ashamed of them.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>I Am Autistic</h2>

<p>My official diagnosis is actually Asperger’s Syndrome, but as of the release of the DSM-V in May 2013, that got rolled into the “official” Autism name. It never really wasn’t part of the Autism Spectrum, but now it just goes by the name High Functioning Autism. Either way, it means that I can blend in with others most of the time, but still relate better to the little boy who freaks out at the crying baby, runs to a corner, and starts rocking back and forth.</p>

<p>In his talk, Greg brought up the “Hunter-Farmer hypothesis,” which is commonly used to explain the origin of ADHD. It’s an interesting theory that basically states that such differences in neurological functioning were not only beneficial, but arguably <em>essential</em> when we were hunter-gatherers, but that since we settled down and started farming, those differences started becoming maladaptive. Those with ADHD now would have been the hunters then, with laser focus under pressure, and bursts of high activity. They may have even been able to “fly under the radar” for generations as soldiers, which experience the same kind of peak and trough routine (or as Greg put it, “War has been described as long periods of boredom punctuated by moments of sheer terror.”), and it’s only very recently, when we’ve all been forced to sit still for hours on end from the time we’re five years old, that it’s become a problem, and since it started becoming a problem, it has exploded in our faces.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='If ADHD people are hunters and soldiers, then Autistics are the foragers and artisans.'>
If ADHD people are hunters and soldiers, then Autistics are the foragers and artisans.
</span></p>

<p>There is a hypthesis that parallels ADHD-as-hunter, known as the <a href="http://www.epjournal.net/wp-content/uploads/EP09207238.pdf">Solitary Forager Hypthesis</a>. In it, Jared Reser explores the idea that some of the common symptoms of Autism &mdash; repetition, rote memorization, obsession over things modern society deems trivial &mdash; may have been highly beneficial traits in hunter-gatherer times. Additionally, the Autistic’s ability to work alone and not be wholly dependent on social groups may have been advantageous, especially in tribes that lived in places where foraging took the individuals far and away from each other for great lengths of time. Like those with ADHD were probably able to find their niches until very recently, I think so did Autistics, in the form of artisans, scholars, and monks &mdash; who spent their entire lives replicating things, doing the same thing over and over, and meticulously honing their craft in a near-obsessive way, with some going so far as to not talk to others and taking a vow of silence.</p>

<p>Reser concludes with this, which I think is a phenomenal philosophy for not just Autism, but ADHD and several other neuro-atypical states:</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='It should not be thought of as something to be ashamed of'>
Showing that autism had ecological viability and that it exists today because of its success in the past suggests that it should not be considered a disease, but instead a condition. It should not be thought of as something to be ashamed of , but as something that represents individuality, self-determination and autonomy.
</span></p>

<h2>I Also Have Depression</h2>

<p>The outpouring of awareness support for mental illness in the wake of Robin Williams&#8217; death has sparked a rise, especially in the developer community, of efforts to end the stigma around mental illness, so that those with them don’t feel ashamed to seek help. I am no exception for either giving or needing to receive that support, and I hope this marks a more permanent rise in such movements than what past losses have seen.</p>

<p>I was diagnosed with Depressive Disorder Not Otherwise Specified (DD-NOS) after a late-term miscarriage that, for all intents and purposes, shattered every fiber of my being. That event not only turned me into a vastly different (and unfortunately, more fragile) person, but it exacerbated what was already there.</p>

<p>The truth of the matter is that I’ve suffered from Depression to one degree or another for about as long as I can remember. Whether it was slowly ingrained into me by a life surrounded by abusive people, both peers and those in positions of authority, or if it was there first and just painted a target on my back for those people, I don’t know. Frankly, it doesn’t matter anymore.</p>

<p>Even when I was younger, the thought of suicide had crossed my mind on more than one occasion, and in recent years, such thoughts have increased in frequency, though I’ve always been too selfless to actually go through with it, because I don’t want to upset my family, and don’t want to put the stress of things like a funeral and being a single father on my husband. It’s not that I think suicide is a “selfish” act &mdash; I don’t believe it is &mdash; but rather that I’m not a very selfish or self-serving person by nature. I’m driven to please others or feel “needed” or “useful.” Something like suicide is the polar opposite to that, and, therefore, takes a considerable amount of effort just to do it. It probably also helps that I end up over-thinking and, in a sense, “over-engineering” my way out of actually going through with it.</p>

<p>I mention the miscarriage, because that’s really also something else that needs to be talked about more. Did you know that the miscarriage rate is upwards of 50% of all pregnancies when chemical pregnancies and other very early miscarriages are taken into account? I didn’t know that, either, until 2006. Even excluding those, the miscarriage rate for Western society is still about 20%. In other words, for every 5 women you know, one of them will have miscarried a known pregnancy. Late term miscarriages &mdash; any that happen betmaween 12 and 24 weeks &mdash; have a rate of 1 in 100, and stillbirths &mdash; after 24 weeks &mdash; have a rate of 1 in 160. This means that odds are very good that you’ve met at least one woman who has lost a pregnancy. And yet, how many of us know the people that have suffered through this? This is why we need to talk more about it, especially since late term miscarriages and stillbirths are particularly devastating.</p>

<p>At that point, you’ve bonded with your unborn child. You’ve probably already had a baby shower. The nursery’s almost done, you’re part way through those birthing classes. You’ve seen the “big” ultrasound. And then, one day, everything grinds to a screeching, horrific, agonizing halt.</p>

<p>But it doesn’t end there, and this is one of those things that really no one talks about. For most sudden traumatic events, the actual event is over relatively quickly, and once it’s done, you can focus on healing, possibly with the help of painkillers. It doesn’t work that way for a woman that experiences a late-term loss, because the body still goes through the postnatal motions <em>as though nothing bad has happened.</em> This includes lactating. The worst pain in the world &mdash; producing milk for an infant that isn’t there &mdash; there are no painkillers for that two weeks of hell.</p>

<p>Yes, this was very much my breaking point, and the best image I have for it is quite literally a glass item dropping and shattering into a few million pieces. It’s a shame <em>Eragon</em> the movie didn’t hold true to the books, or the shattering of the Star Sapphire at the Battle of Farthen Dur would have been a perfect image for those who haven’t gone through such a loss (as it stands, it’s still a perfect metaphor). Unfortunately, unlike the dwarves in <em>Eragon</em>, we don’t have dragon magic to restore us to our former glory, even if we and our fleet of people dedicated to piecing us back together could manage to do so.</p>

<p>Like <a href="https://medium.com/@kayladnls/youre-not-alone-f210b82893cb">a good friend of mine, Kayla,</a> related, there are a number of times where I’ve sat alone and cried, or cried myself to sleep. Sometimes, there may be a trigger &mdash; not a reason, per se, but rather, something that starts the chain reaction. Maybe it’s a bad day at work, a fight with my husband, or my mind replaying real or imagined horrors. Other times, there’s no known reason at all, just the nothingness itself weighing down on me.</p>

<h2>I’m Not Alone</h2>

<p><a href="http://archive.wired.com/wired/archive/9.12/aspergers_pr.html">Wired Magazine</a> nailed it way back in 2004: the stereotypical “geek” is more likely to be on the Autism Spectrum (and therefore have kids who are also on the Spectrum). And it’s true, computers and electronics, and the professional fields that revolve around them, attract people with varying levels of Autism. I suspect that it largely has to do with the fact that technology itself (and math in general) is based on clear-cut rules and standards, and those rules and standards usually have a reason behind them. There may be a hundred ways to solve a problem, but all of those ways still require laying out a set of rules to achieve an end. Technology <em>makes sense</em> in a world that is otherwise run by arbitrary nonsense to us. So, if you work in, or in any way interact with people who work in, technology, odds are, you’ve met someone with Autism, even if you didn’t realize it.</p>

<p>Even if you aren’t involved at all with anything technology-related, with the Autism diagnostic rate somewhere between 1 in 50 and 1 in 68 (depending on who you ask), odds are, you’ve met someone with Autism. And since not everyone with Autism gravitates toward technology, it may even be that new artist you saw at your local gallery, or the odd neighbor kid.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='*tech culture attracts the oddities that are a result of mental illness*'>
To compound matters, there’s also the fact, as Greg mentions in his talk on Devs and Depression, that tech attracts the people most prone to mental illness in general. As such, while the numbers are a lot more fuzzy, there’s <a href="http://tpr.org/post/geeks-depression-highlighting-mental-health-issues-tech-community">little doubt that our industry has a high rate of people with Depression, Bipolar, and other mental illnesses</a>, if for no other reason than that <em>tech culture attracts the oddities that are a result of mental illness</em> (as Greg said in his talk, “we accept introverted behavior, odd sleeping patterns, inconsistent bursts of productivity, and a sense of grandiosity… we are your people”).
</span></p>

<h2>What Does It All Mean?</h2>

<p>For me, it means I’ve got a witty, no-holds-barred, sarcastic, confident woman trapped inside a fearful, anxiety-filled body and brain. I can’t count the number of times I’ve imagined a conversation &mdash; any conversation &mdash; where I’d be able to make some kind of witty response, or even just stand up for myself without shutting down, and actually succeed at doing so.</p>

<p>I’ve had a running theory that Autism is largely and input/output disorder &mdash; the common threads in nearly all Autistics is difficulty processing input (sensory overload, slow auditory processing, etc), and difficulty turning it into output (difficulty with spoken conversation, not showing emotion, etc). As such, there are a number of myths that have formed, as researchers and doctors try to make sense of Autism and help people with it. I’ll go into detail another time, as there’s a lot to be said on the matter, but I’ll touch on some of the things in a moment.</p>

<p>My personal history with both Autism and Depression have made me a very self-aware kind of person. This is very much a double-edge sword, because I can see where failure points are, but don’t always have the knowledge or means of <em>correcting</em> said failure points. In other words, I can see <em>that</em> something is failing (usually communication), but I can’t figure out <em>why</em> or what to do about it or even to mitigate the resulting issues. This occasionally leads to a negative feedback loop, where the Depression starts to take over in the form of despair for being able to get things right.</p>

<h3>Okay, But What Does It <em>Mean</em>?</h3>

<p>Waxing philosophical about the ups and downs of both matters is a great pass time, but what does it mean for those around me, in day-to-day interactions?</p>

<p>Well, first, let me address some misconceptions of primarily Autism, and to a lesser extent, Depression:</p>

<ul>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I am violent, prone to violence, or will become a serial killer (or any other form of murderer).</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I am mentally disabled.</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I lack empathy or have no feelings, though I may feel and express them differently from other people.</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that my Autism in need of a “cure,” or that I otherwise need “fixed.” My Depression may be a mental illness, but my Autism is not, and there is a difference.</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I’m constantly under suicide watch or that I’d do something drastic just because someone said something I didn’t like.</li>
<li><p>If I happen to be on antidepressants at the time, it <strong>does not</strong> mean that I have to be happy all the time, or that the medication is not working if I show even the slightest hint of a negative emotion.</p></li>
<li><p>It <strong>does</strong> mean that I communicate better through asynchronous means (writing, as opposed to speaking), for a multitude of reasons.</p></li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that sometimes I will get overstressed and need to remove myself from the situation, and that when that happens, I need enough respect and compassion from others to give me some space and time.</li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that I do better knowing things ahead of time, such as changes in schedules or meeting agendas (especially when said meeting is prone to be emotionally charged or critical of me/my work).</li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that, particularly when it comes to social infractions, I genuinely may not know what has upset someone, and telling me “you’re smart, you can figure it out,” does not help me.</li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that I will <em>always</em> prioritize the things that help me <em>above all else</em>. This includes proper diet and exercise, and the means and time to achieve those. This also means that I am <em>very protective</em> of my work-life balance, and will strive to ensure that I’m not working more than I can handle. My ability to stop working at a reasonable hour so that I can participate in that day’s workout and cook my dinner as opposed to ordering pizza and soda is what allows me to be productive each day and keep working on the things that make my employer money. No job is worth my well-being, especially since sacrificing the latter will inevitably sacrifice the former.</li>
</ul>


<h2>What Can We Do?</h2>

<h3>Recognize That Not Everyone Who Is Sick Looks So</h3>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='It’s the phrase just about everyone with an invisible illness has heard from anyone who knows but doesn’t understand their situation &#8211; “but you don’t *look* sick.”'>
Mental illness, like many physical illnesses, manifest in ways that most of society deems, from the outside looking in, as character flaws. According to society, or anyone that doesn’t experience it themselves, we don’t do something not because we’re sick and are physically incapable of doing that thing, but because we’re “lazy” or “unmotivated.” It’s the phrase just about everyone with an invisible illness has heard from anyone who knows but doesn’t understand their situation &mdash; “but you don’t <em>look</em> sick.”
</span></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Twerkerella/status/501230591615201281/photo/1">This image illustrates the problem quite well</a>, as does <a href="http://www.butyoudontlooksick.com/wpress/articles/written-by-christine/the-spoon-theory/">this story</a>, for those more inclined for words.</p>

<p>If you do not suffer from an invisible illness, recognize that just because you can’t <em>see</em> the symptoms, it doesn’t mean they’re not there. They are very much there, very much real, and those of us with them spend every waking moment doing what we can to keep it from consuming us and our lives. For some of us, the very act of getting out of bed is little short of a miracle. What you see is generally an act or part of a plan to get through the day and meet such needs as earning money.</p>

<p>We’re not being lazy or making excuses when we say we can’t do something. Do you say that a paraplegic is just being lazy by not walking, or a blind person just isn’t trying hard enough at seeing? No? The same applies to mental illness. A person suffering from Depression can’t just “try harder” at being happy. It doesn’t work that way.</p>

<h3>Provide Reasonable Work Hours and Conditions</h3>

<p>If you’re an employer, especially in the tech industry, remember that not everyone is a healthy, single, 20-something who has no life outside of working for you, and that <em>this is not a bad thing.</em> Different people bring different experiences and knowledge to the table, providing valuable input.</p>

<p>Instead of viewing these things as liabilities, view them as assets to be cultivated and nurtured. Really, all people should be treated this way, as no one should have to work ungodly numbers of hours every day. That’s a sure path to destruction of even the healthiest of individuals, though it may take longer.</p>

<p>For those with mental illnesses, it’s better to be able to work shorter hours, which keeps us from long-term destruction, than to run us ragged and destroy us in a few months or, at best, a couple of years. It’s been shown that <em>everyone</em> &mdash; with or without any kind of chronic illness &mdash; does better on shorter hours and that long hours are <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2013/07/09/news/economy/shorter-work-week/">at best useless and at worst counterproductive</a>. There’s a reason labor laws are supposed to limit workers to 40 hours a week (“exempt” status notwithstanding), and those reasons don’t just apply to the blue collar workers for whom such laws are actually enforced.</p>

<h3>Talk</h3>

<p>For those of us with mental illnesses, we can start by talking about it. There are a couple of hashtags floating around Twitter. The main one is <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23endthestigma&amp;src=tyah">#EndTheStigma</a>, which includes not just mental health, but other stigmatized things as well. There’s also a new one rising up, called <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23hackthestigma&amp;src=typd">#HackTheStigma</a>, that was originally created due to not wanting to be associated with the “End The Stigma” campaigns used by some companies.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not ready to talk openly, you can reach out to me or any of the others in the community that have opened their inboxes and/or phones.</p>

<p>We’re here. You’re not alone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lodging With AirBnb]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/05/19/airbnb-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T13:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/05/19/airbnb-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I had the pleasure of going to New York City for <a href="https://conference.laravel.com/">Laracon US</a>. It was a phenomenal experience, but there was one problem &mdash; New York City is bloody expensive. At $250 a night for the group rate, the hotel was no exception, and the disadvantage of being a female in a male-dominated industry is that finding a roommate to share a room with is damn near impossible. So, I was on my own for finding a way to save a little money on lodging. Unfortunately, the traditional booking agencies didn&rsquo;t really have anything that were much of a savings and near to the conference venue.</p>

<h2>Enter AirBnb</h2>

<p>Some of the guys who were involved with last year&rsquo;s Laracon EU introduced me to <a href="https://www.airbnb.com/">AirBnb</a>. It&rsquo;s an interesting concept &mdash; people rent out a room in their home for a given price per night. Generally, this results in a cost savings for the guest, and helps defray the host&rsquo;s cost of their home. AirBnb works like a booking agency, helping guests find and book places to stay; an escrow service, holding the money in the event a refund is needed and ensuring the host gets paid for services rendered; and housekeeping, making sure the room is ready for the guest and in good shape between guests.</p>

<p>I decided to check it out to see what I could find, and I lucked into an opening just <a href="https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/1851350">a couple of blocks away,</a> for about a third of the cost of a stay at the hotel. So, I put in a booking request (hosts can approve or refuse booking requests), and a short while later, my request was approved.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Pre-Flight</h2>

<p>A few days before I was to be in NYC, both AirBnb, and my host, sent a couple of emails that included pertinent information, including how to get to the apartment, how to get into the building, which bedroom to use, and how to open the murphy bed in guest room, as well as a general reminder of the trip itself. To help maintain privacy, details like the exact address are left out until after the booking is confirmed, hence the emails.</p>

<h2>Showtime</h2>

<p>Getting to the apartment was pretty easy. It had been a while, but I&rsquo;ve had some experience with NYC&rsquo;s mass transit system (the Metro Transit Authority, or MTA), so the first thing I did was find an MTA kiosk and pick up a card, then made a beeline to the bus station from LaGuardia Airport (LGA). From there, it was an easy train ride down to Soho, and a short walk to the apartment. It took about an hour to get there, which is, from what I can tell, a pretty average time between LGA and Manhattan.</p>

<p>When I got there, I followed the instructions to get in, and got into the building pretty easily&hellip;to find that his wasn&rsquo;t the only apartment, and it turned out to be a multi-story walk-up. No problem (on review of the description, that was noted, but it seems that the listing changed since I booked, so either I missed it, or it wasn&rsquo;t there before). Not an uncommon occurrence in Manhattan buildings. It&rsquo;s definitely an older building, with narrow, steep stairs indicative of 19th century (or so) architecture. As a young, decently fit adult, I didn&rsquo;t mind, but it is something to consider/ask about if one has any kind of issues that would make such a setup an issue.</p>

<p>The apartment itself was a pleasant contrast to the stairwell. It was still small and narrow, but it had been recently updated, making it a fairly attractive place to stay. I was told that the guest bedroom (which was teal in color) was &ldquo;to the left.&rdquo; Well, technically, it was more like &ldquo;around the corner,&rdquo; but it&rsquo;s not like a 500sqft apartment is easy to get lost in, and the one other bedroom was very much not teal.</p>

<p>So, I go over to the other door and&hellip;it&rsquo;s locked. Odd, but it&rsquo;s one of those locks that&rsquo;s unlocked by a coin. I find one and go in to find stuff in it. It looks like someone else is staying there. Again, this seems odd. There was never any mention made that I wasn&rsquo;t the only guest (I was under the impression that the host was renting out his spare room, and therefore would be occupying his bedroom). So, I pinged him via email, stashed my stuff, and went on my way as I was meeting with others.</p>

<p>A short while later, he emailed me that yes, indeed, there was another guest there, and I was to actually have the not-teal bedroom. As it turned out, the host wasn&rsquo;t in town at all and was renting out both rooms that week. That would have been nice to know, but really, it&rsquo;s my only real complaint, and it was straightened out with a couple of emails. Besides, it worked out largely in my favor, because I got a real bed, and not a murphy bed. Since I was using the place solely as a crash pad, and would be spending my waking hours elsewhere, the fact that I was sharing the common areas with someone else was a non-issue, and the bed was the most important feature for me.</p>

<p>From what I could tell, the murphy bed in the teal bedroom was a full bed, with a small couch for extra sleeping if needed. Not a ton of space, but enough to sleep a couple of people pretty comfortably, with some space for luggage. The other bedroom was large enough to fit a queen bed and some typical bedroom furniture, which noticeably more walking space, making it the roomier of the two rooms. A couple of large windows allow quite a bit of natural light in &mdash; which is great except for the part where it wakes the light sleeper early in the morning (actually, not a terrible thing, as it served as a great alarm clock for me to be up in time to have a leisurely breakfast with my friends before the conference started for the day; I&rsquo;ll take <em>it</em> over a blaring alarm clock). They did also let sound in pretty easily, and since it&rsquo;s in the middle of downtown Manhattan, that means the usual city sounds. Those who are used to rural areas may have a hard time sleeping, but coming from a not-so-quiet city, myself, along with long days on the town and walking everywhere made it a non-issue for me.</p>

<p>Like the apartment as a whole, the bathroom was <em>really</em> small. Now, I&rsquo;m used to small bathrooms. The combined floor space of my three bathrooms is all of 80 square feet (I can floor the largest one with a single box of flooring). But this one made even mine look large. If you&rsquo;re a large person, expect to have to step into the tub to be able to close the door, because it opens inward, and there&rsquo;s only enough floor space for the door to clear the toilet and sink, and for one&rsquo;s knees when sitting on the toilet. It&rsquo;s a tight fit, to say the least. Works for me, though, because it leaves more space for more important rooms &mdash; in this case, bedrooms. I do kind of feel bad for the other guest, as the teal bedroom was right next to the bathroom, so I doubt my early morning showers were all that welcome. At least the front door was away from that bedroom, so they weren&rsquo;t as likely to be disturbed by my coming in at all hours of the night. No doubt they wondered whether I got any amount of sleep at all, or if I was just a suitcase that showed up randomly and disappeared just as randomly.</p>

<h3>Overall Thoughts</h3>

<p>All in all, it was a good experience, and largely went as expected &mdash; I rented a bedroom in which I could crash for a couple of hours a night for a few nights. The host was great and readily responded to my questions. The location was about as perfect as I could get for my needs. The bed was comfortable and the apartment was clean. If you&rsquo;re looking to stay in New York City, I definitely recommend checking out AirBnb in general, and this Soho apartment, specifically.</p>

<p>(P.S. &mdash; If you want to use AirBnb, either for booking or for hosting, <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/sgordon52">have a referral link</a> for a $25USD credit toward your next reservation on AirBnb.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project - Raze West Virginia]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/11/17/project-raze-west-virginia/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T14:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/11/17/project-raze-west-virginia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The Client, and a Little History</h2>

<p>While working at Fahlgren Mortine, I had the opportunity to work with the West Virginia Department of Health and Human Resources (DHHR) on the new website for their teen anti-tobacco campaign, Raze West Virgina.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m already familiar with teen anti-tobacco campaigns, having been involved in Pennsylvania&rsquo;s for a time when I was a teen, myself, but I found out that what makes West Virginia&rsquo;s somewhat unique &ndash; and very important &ndash; is that West Virginia ranks as the highest, or second highest (in some subcategories), of tobacco users nearly across the board, from adults, to pregnant women, to teens. When nearly a third of everyone around you, no matter the demographic, uses tobacco, that&rsquo;s a lot of peer pressure.</p>

<h3>Enter Raze</h3>

<p>Raze is one of several youth anti-tobacco campaigns in West Virginia. It&rsquo;s a little different from many others, because it&rsquo;s not just conferences. Rather, it&rsquo;s groups of teens at the school and community levels (&ldquo;crews&rdquo;), sponsored by an adult, that help create a grassroots anti-tobacco movement. They do this by organizing what they call &ldquo;commotions,&rdquo; or micro-events to help raise awareness and &ldquo;tear down tobacco lies.&rdquo; These commotions can be as simple as handing out fliers, or as large as holding an assembly.</p>

<p>As an added incentive, organizing commotions earns the crew a certain number of points. At various thresholds, the crew then earns gear, ranging from pens to backpacks, emblazoned with the Raze logo.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Our Role</h3>

<p>As West Virginia DHHR&rsquo;s advertising campaign provider, Fahlgren Mortine was provided a number of tasks in an effort to rebrand the Raze campaign. Among them, was redoing the website and crew management system.</p>

<h2>The Challenge</h2>

<p>Raze had an existing crew management system and public-facing website, but it was getting old, and had become unweildly to maintain and use. They needed something more modern, more robust, and easier to use and manage. They needed something tailored to their needs, instead of an off-the-shelf solution that needed to be hacked around and have dozens of add-ons tacked on.</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Instead of going with another off-the-shelf solution, we decided to build a custom system from the ground up. This would allow us to provide them with only what they need, and provide it when they need it.</p>

<h3>The Tech</h3>

<p>In order to keep the codebase maintainable, we used the MVC framework, <a href="http://laravel.com/">Laravel</a>, as the backbone of the application. Combined with the PHP package management system, <a href="http://getcomposer.org/">Composer</a>, this allows us to swap out certain parts (particularly third-party libraries) nearly at will, without much consequence to the application as a whole.</p>

<p><a class="right" href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/images/portfolio/raze_announcement_tooltip.jpg" title="The Dashboard page" target="_blank"><img src="http://ShaunaGordon.com/images/portfolio/thumbs/raze_announcement_tooltip.jpg" alt="Stylized tooltips to add that application feel" /></a></p>

<p>To make development of the interface faster and easier, the dashboard interface was built with the help of <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap</a>. This allowed us to spend less time on building interface components and making them look good, and more time putting them together into a user-friendly interface. It also allowed us to add small garnishes, such as stylized tooltips, for browsers that support the extra features.</p>

<p>Even with the help of Bootstrap and Laravel, we still found ourselves using quite a bit of JavaScript, as well as a fair amount of CSS customization. To help keep these maintainable, and to allow us to generate minimized JavaScript and CSS files, we used the CSS preprocessor, <a href="http://sass-lang.com/">Sass</a>, and the <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a>-based task runner, <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">Grunt</a>.</p>

<h3>The Logic</h3>

<p>While we also redid the public facing site (<a href="https://razewv.com">razewv.com</a>), the dashboard interface at <a href="https://razewv.com/manage">razewv.com/manage</a> is where the bulk of the work, and the heavy lifting, are done.</p>

<p><a class="left" href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/images/portfolio/raze_dashboard.jpg" title="The Dashboard page" target="_blank"><img src="http://ShaunaGordon.com/images/portfolio/thumbs/raze_dashboard.jpg" alt="The Raze Dashboard" /></a></p>

<p>At its core, it&rsquo;s a user and event management system. Adults and students sign up and join their crews. Adult advisors and crew leaders can schedule commotions based on pretermined choices, and can register for region and organization-wide events (such as Regional Raze Kickoff Events). When the commotions are completed and logged, the system tallies up the crew&rsquo;s total points, and standing compared to other crews, based on the point values of the commotions they performed.</p>

<p>Site Administrators can also generate reports for various statistics, in addition to taking suggestions for, and adding, new commotions, scheduling events, and sending announcements.</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>This was one of our first built-from-scratch content management systems, so one of the biggest lessons was that such systems are quite a bit larger than they appear.</p>

<p>It was a fun project, though, and really allowed us to stretch our legs when it came to Laravel. It also allowed us to start incorporating some of the automation capabilities of Grunt, which will prove to be invaluable in future projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vagrant - Initial Thoughts]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/11/17/vagrant-initial-thoughts/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T01:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/11/17/vagrant-initial-thoughts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I finally did it. I finally started playing with <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>. I have to say, I quite like it.</p>

<p>At the moment, I just have a generic Ubuntu box that I downloaded from <a href="http://www.vagrantbox.es/">Vagrentboxes</a> and then used a script to download the dependencies needed to run Octopress and my blog. Add a little port-forwarding magic, and I no longer have to deal with RVM, Ruby versions, and what-have-you on my MacBook Pro (this is a very good thing, as I&rsquo;ve found OSX to be surprisingly hostile to developers in its attempt to be &ldquo;helpful&rdquo;). This is great, but quite cumbersome, because it involves updating apt-get, installing a bunch of things that have a laundry list of dependencies out of apt-get, then installing the Ruby gems needed, <em>then</em>, finally, running <code>rake preview</code>. Once it&rsquo;s up and running, it&rsquo;s great, but that process takes somewhere between 5 and 10 minutes.</p>

<p>Come on now, we can do better than that.</p>

<p>So, now, my next project with Vagrant will be to create a box that already has the necessary prerequisites for Octopress. Then, at some point, I think I&rsquo;ll make one for other development projects, too. I suspect it will save me &ndash; and some of my coworkers &ndash; quite a bit of headache when it comes to dealing with different development environments (I know at least one coworker who has to support legacy 5.3 applications, and help with our new Laravel apps that require 5.4+ due to our heavy usage of array literal notation).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[box-sizing: border-box and Changes in How We Use the Box Model]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/02/19/box-sizing-border-box-and-changes-in-how-we-use-the-box-model/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/02/19/box-sizing-border-box-and-changes-in-how-we-use-the-box-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in the days when Internet Explorer 6 reigned supreme, when Firefox was just getting its foothold and taking shares from IE, and Chrome was barely a Googler&rsquo;s pet project, the browsers followed different box models.</p>

<p>Firefox (as well as the then little-known browsers Opera and Safari) followed the W3C standard box model, what is now known as &ldquo;content-box&rdquo;. Internet Explorer, on the other hand, followed its own box model, what we now call &ldquo;border-box&rdquo;. As Firefox began to rise and threatened IE&rsquo;s market share, Web developers were singing the praises of the content-box style box model (which was one of the many W3C standards that IE ignored, and Firefox implemented), to the point that when Microsoft finally released Internet Explorer 7, it implemented the standard box model.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Fast forward seven years</h2>

<p>Now, it&rsquo;s 2013, not only are more browsers on the market, but the market share has tipped dramatically away from Internet Explorer, and had spread out among several browsers. Competition has forced IE to be more standards compliant (IE10 even has text shadow support!). And, to top it all off, a CSS technique is on the rise: <code>box-sizing: border-box</code>. Yes, the very same method that IE6 used.</p>

<h3>What changed?</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m only speculating, but I think it&rsquo;s a fundamental shift in how developers write both HTML and CSS &mdash; and perhaps a refinement of what they feel the standards should be &mdash; based on what works and what makes sense in practice. There are two main paradigm &ldquo;camps&rdquo; regarding how HTML and CSS should be architected and written.</p>

<p>The first is the &ldquo;positional&rdquo; camp. The idea behind this one is that an element&rsquo;s style should be dictated by it&rsquo;s position in the document object model, or DOM. So, for example, all <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> elements within any <code>&lt;nav&gt;</code> element would have <code>display: inline-block</code> applied to them (making a horizontal navigation list), but if you moved that same set if <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> elements into an <code>&lt;article&gt;</code> element, it would become a vertical list.</p>

<p>The other is the &ldquo;object oriented&rdquo; camp. The idea here is that the <code>&lt;ul&gt;</code> (unordered list) which is the parent of the above-mentioned <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> elements, would have one or more classes on them, such as &ldquo;horizontal&rdquo; or &ldquo;main-nav&rdquo;. This class, or set of classes, would dictate how the block of elements would look, regardless of where the block was placed. To use the same example, all <code>&lt;li&gt;</code> elements within the <code>&lt;ul class="main-nav"&gt;</code> block woud have <code>display: inline-block</code> on them. This styling would stay the same regardless of whether the block was inside a <code>&lt;nav&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;article&gt;</code> element.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='OOCSS creates modularity and allows for code reuse'>
In recent years, the trend has been shifting more toward this &ldquo;object oriented CSS&rdquo; camp, and for good reason &ndash; OOCSS creates modularity and allows for code reuse. This allows, for example, for me to reuse my <a href="https://gist.github.com/4033366">faux image frame effect</a> on just about any element block on any website, simply by dropping in the required CSS and adding the &ldquo;framed&rdquo; class to whatever I want to have the frame.
</span></p>

<p>One of the rules of object oriented design is that an object shouldn&rsquo;t care about any objects outside of itself. Each object handles itself and the initial creation of its children (the children then handle themselves). This isn&rsquo;t as rigid in CSS as it is in real programming languages, due to how CSS and document flow manipulation works, but the logic is still sound and works for the most part.</p>

<p>However, <code>box-sizing: content-box</code> (the default box-sizing for modern browsers) breaks this rule, by, in a sense, making objects lie about their true size.</p>

<p>For example, let&rsquo;s say I have a three-column layout, and I want each column to be equal width. Okay, that&rsquo;s easy, we do something like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Our 3-Column Layout</span><a href='http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/'>jsFiddle </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">&quot;wrapper&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">&quot;three-column&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      Some content
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">&quot;three-column&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      Some content
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">&quot;three-column&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>      Some content
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Our 3-Column Layout&#8217;s CSS</span><a href='http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/'>jsFiddle </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='css'><span class='line'><span class="nc">.wrapper</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">width</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">960px</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* Some arbitrary bounding. 960px is usually the width of fixed-width layouts. */</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">width</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">33</span><span class="o">%</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* 100%/3 = ~33% */</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">height</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">200px</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* Stick in an arbitrary height for display purposes. */</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">float</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">left</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">background</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">#f00</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* Red, again for display purposes */</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span><span class="nd">:first-child</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">background</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">#0f0</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* Green, to show the column differences */</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span><span class="nd">:last-child</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">background</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">#00f</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* Blue, to show the column differences */</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This gives us a nice little three-column layout:</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/embedded/result/light/"></iframe>


<p>This is great! But we&rsquo;d like some breathing room between the ends of the text and the edges of their blocks, like so:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Let&#8217;s Add Padding</span><a href='http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/1'>jsFiddle </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='css'><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c">/* Existing code */</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">padding</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">0</span> <span class="m">5px</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* 0 top and bottom padding, 5px left and right padding */</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look now!</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/1/embedded/result/light/"></iframe>


<p>Uh oh! That&rsquo;s not what we want. What happened? The boxes should only be 33% of the width!</p>

<p>You&rsquo;d think that, wouldn&rsquo;t you? Remember what I said earlier about <code>box-sizing: content-box</code> making liars out of our elements? Well, this is it. You see, &ldquo;33%&rdquo; is only the width of the <em>content</em>. That doesn&rsquo;t include margins, padding, or borders.</p>

<p>For most people (particularly the OOCSS-leaning people we mentioned earlier), this <em>really</em> doesn&rsquo;t make sense for padding. The purpose of padding is to add space from the outer edge, or border, of the container, in to the content. Basically the same way the margin lines on a piece of notebook paper work. Logically, this should reduce the space allotted to the content (likewise, the CSS margin would be roughly equivalent to the space between pages in an opened notebook &ndash; they exist outside the bounds of the edge of the container). Why, then, is the default behavior to make the box <em>bigger</em> when either margin or padding is added?</p>

<p>Now, in the days of fixed-width layouts, this meant recalculating the width of the internal boxes, so that they fit within their parent. This is one of the core reasons why 960px was used as the go-to content width of fixed layouts &ndash; 960 divides into both 2 and 3 evenly (1, 2, and 3 columns being the most common layouts). So, in the days of the fixed-width layout, we&rsquo;d simply change the width of our boxes to accommodate things like margins, padding, and borders:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Now, Fix the Damn Layout</span><a href='http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/4'>jsFiddle </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='css'><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c">/* width: 33%; */</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">width</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">310px</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* 960px/3 = 320px, 320px-15px (5px left padding + 5px right padding) = 310px */</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And look! Our layout works again!</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/4/embedded/result/light/"></iframe>


<p>But what happens when the width of the container is proportional, and scales based on the browser size, as with fluid layouts? Well, our layout breaks again, because it&rsquo;s dependent on a parent width of 960px. Once that parent width drops below 960px, our columns wrap again. Now, in some instances, this may be what we want (when a viewport gets too narrow, having columns drop underneath one another can help keep them wide enough to be readable), but we generally want some kind of give before that happens.</p>

<p>Okay, so we want the columns to scale with their parent (at least to certain breakpoints, but that&rsquo;s a discussion for a different time), <em>and</em> we want the fixed-sized padding, is there a way to do that? Well, before <code>box-sizing: border-box</code> gained support, there actually was, but it wasn&rsquo;t all that pretty, especially when dealing with pixel-perfectionists. You just used percentages for everything:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Back to fluid?</span><a href='http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/3'>jsFiddle </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='css'><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">width</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">32</span><span class="o">%</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">padding</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">0</span> <span class="o">.</span><span class="m">5</span><span class="o">%</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/3/embedded/result/light/"></iframe>


<p>This works great&hellip;except for the fact that the padding also expands or contracts. If that&rsquo;s what you want, then great! If you&rsquo;re like me, and have to deal with people who expect those padding to stay the same, then you&rsquo;re <abbr title="Shit out of Luck">SoL</abbr> (or, at least, you used to be).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also possible to put the margins or padding on the child elements, but that would either require an extra &ldquo;wrapper&rdquo; element, or some not-so-ideal <code>.three-column *</code> type selectors. Both of these options work, but are ugly and not very elegant. Plus, you&rsquo;d have to do that for everything that is affected by this issue, instead of just making it do something sane to begin with.</p>

<h2>This sounds like a job for&hellip;.!</h2>

<p>With <code>box-sizing: border-box</code>, you can now use the percentage widths, with fixed-sized padding, to get this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Box-sizing to the rescue!</span><a href='http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/5'>jsFiddle </a></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='css'><span class='line'><span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">moz</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">box</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">sizing</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">border</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">box</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="c">/* Firefox still uses the prefixed version */</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">box</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">sizing</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">border</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">box</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nc">.three-column</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">width</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">33</span><span class="o">%</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">padding</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="m">0</span> <span class="m">5px</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 300px" frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" src="http://jsfiddle.net/gordondev/yzfH2/5/embedded/result/light/"></iframe>


<p>Yay! And look, this actually makes sense (to most people)! If I tell the element that I want it to be 33% of its parent, that means I want the <em>everything</em> within the element&rsquo;s borders to be 33% of its parent.</p>

<h2>I said all that to say this&hellip;</h2>

<p>As you can see, with the standard <code>box-sizing: content-box</code>, making flexibile layouts is a nightmare, especially when trying to keep things lean for our mobile-device-using friends. The shift toward responsive and flexible layouts has necessitated a need for stricter adherence to object-oriented types of rules, for the sake of our sanity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project: Octopress Theme Toytown]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/25/project-octopress-theme-toytown/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-25T09:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/25/project-octopress-theme-toytown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of yet another redesign and blog migration, I needed to create a theme that wasn&rsquo;t so stock. I migrated my site to <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, a blogging platform that runs on GitHub&rsquo;s <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> static site generator. It&rsquo;s a great platform, as anyone who follows my Twitter or Google+ accounts is aware, but the vast majority of sites that run on Octopress use the default theme, or some slight variation thereof. As good and nice as the default theme is, it&rsquo;s become very generic. I needed something different.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why &ldquo;Toytown&rdquo;?</h2>

<p>The entire theme is based around the image in the background. That image is actually one of the views I get to see in the mornings and evenings when I go to and leave from work.</p>

<p>You see, my office is located in one of the biggest shopping districts in the city, and it&rsquo;s pretty unique in that it&rsquo;s built as a blend between an indoor shopping mall and street-facing shops. Every year for the holidays (and evidently, well into the new year, for whatever reason), they string up lights on every building. It always reminds me of a gingerbread town, because of the way the lights are done &ndash; it&rsquo;s &ldquo;warm&rdquo; white rope lights lined along the corners and some other accent lines, much the same way you&rsquo;d have the frosting on a gingerbread building. They also have a couple of giant Christmas trees in the main open areas to the north and south of the main &ldquo;mall&rdquo; area. I have no doubt that, if viewed from above, in, say, a helicopter, it would look more like something you&rsquo;d find in a toy or model train store than an actual shopping center.</p>

<h2>The Keystone of the Theme</h2>

<p>Combine the natural &ldquo;toy-like&rdquo; aspect of the area this time of year, with the view from a few dozen feet above ground level, and a little manipulation in Gimp to create a <a href="http://www.inspiration.scottphotographics.com/amazing-miniature-tilt-shift-photography/">tilt-shift miniature effect</a>, and you end up with a fun background that looks more like a model than a real place.</p>

<p>The first image I had of it wasn&rsquo;t as high quality as I&rsquo;d like, due to having taken it with my smartphone, especially at the scale needed to adequately make it a background for a website. So, as much as I loved the image itself (because it was late enough in the morning to be &ldquo;daytime&rdquo;, but you could still see the lights on the buildings), I decided to go out and take more pictures, this time with an actual camera. (Note: as of 1/25/13, the &ldquo;first image&rdquo; is still the one used. I don&rsquo;t have access to an SD card reader at the moment, so I can&rsquo;t get the pictures off of my camera.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also this image that I derived the color theme from, with the aid of the wonderfully useful <a href="http://colorschemedesigner.com">Color Scheme Designer</a>. The entire theme actually consists of just three base colors, with which I played with shades, hues, and opacity to achieve the desired effects.</p>

<p>Ah, the joys of working in the digital realm.</p>

<h2>Layout</h2>

<p>Since it&rsquo;s largely a blog these days (I still have my &ldquo;About&rdquo; page, which has the online version of my resume and will eventually sport the download options, as well, but the main focal point is the blog), I decided to stick with the two-column theme, allowing for various supplementary things, such as recent or related posts, tag clouds, and so forth.</p>

<p>Additionally, I&rsquo;ve made the site responsive. Anything above a 920px wide screen (or its rought equivalent, as it also responds to text size; more on that later), will have a single-column experience, with the extra goodies at the bottom. As the viewport gets smaller, some items will even shift their layout entirely, to accommodate the typical touch input of what are typically smaller screens. I also drop out the background image entirely (or rather, I don&rsquo;t add it in until larger sizes), to help keep bandwidth lower on devices that are more likely to be on a connection where download size is important.</p>

<h2>320 and Up? Kind of.</h2>

<p>One of the big new paradigms in web development is what&rsquo;s known as &ldquo;mobile first&rdquo; development. Among the large frameworks and bootstrapping tools is <a href="http://www.stuffandnonsense.co.uk/blog/about/this_is_the_new_320_and_up">320 and Up</a>, which starts its <abbr title="Cascading Style Sheets">CSS</abbr> media query &ldquo;breakpoints&rdquo; with 320px wide (the most narrow viewport size that most modern smartphones use) and work up from there.
<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='mobile devices lie about their pixel width'>
But there&rsquo;s a major problem with it, and every other mobile-first framework out there currently &ndash; mobile devices lie about their pixel width. This is in part because a pixel isn&rsquo;t always a pixel. You see, in <abbr title="Cascading Style Sheets">CSS</abbr>, the unit &ldquo;pixel&rdquo; is actually a <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/css3-values/#reference-pixel">standardized measurement</a> based on the average viewing distance of the object (and actually, <a href="http://www.quirksmode.org/blog/archives/2012/11/the_css_physica.html">all CSS units of measurement are based on this &ldquo;reference pixel&rdquo;</a>), whereas, in most other computer contexts (including images), a pixel is the smallest unit of measurement for a digital display. Until fairly recently, computers displayed at a pixel density of around 96<abbr title="Dots Per Inch">DPI</abbr>, making 1 CSS pixel roughly equivalent to 1 device pixel.
</span>
Until 1px no longer equals 1px.</p>

<p>This is exactly what we&rsquo;re seeing with the new high-density (&ldquo;retina&rdquo;) displays, which have upwards of two or more times the number of Dots Per Inch as a 96<abbr title="Dots Per Inch">DPI</abbr> screen. To compound matters, these new devices don&rsquo;t have the same pixel densities. In fact, their densities are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_displays_by_pixel_density#Devices_by_manufacturers">all over the map</a>. 151, 132, 202, etc. Even if you go off of the &ldquo;CSS pixel ratio&rdquo;, you still have 1, 1.325, 1.5, 2, and who-knows-what else in the future (and you <em>know</em> not all of the real pixel densities match well to the &ldquo;CSS pixel ratio&rdquo;).</p>

<p>Oh yeah, and, in part because of the above, these devices basically lie about their resolutions. The &ldquo;Retina&rdquo; iPhones report their resolutions as half of what they actually are. Additionally, some devices will increase their font size, but report a resolution that looks like a desktop.</p>

<p>So what to do? <a href="http://blog.cloudfour.com/the-ems-have-it-proportional-media-queries-ftw/">How about not use pixel-based media queries to begin with?</a> This has two added bonuses &ndash; you no longer have to worry about CSS pixel to device pixel differences, and you can adjust based on zoom level.</p>

<p>Go ahead, zoom in on the site. Isn&rsquo;t that cool?</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s one of the first projects I&rsquo;ve actually done using the &ldquo;mobile-first&rdquo; paradigm, as well as using EMs, so it could probably use some polish, but it was fun to learn, and it even looks good on my Android devices.</p>

<h2>Other Technologies</h2>

<h3>HTML5 and CSS</h3>

<p>Since it&rsquo;s an Octopress theme, it makes heavy use of HTML5, <a href="http://sass-lang.com">Sass</a>, and <a href="http://compass-style.org/">Compass</a>. I didn&rsquo;t do much with the HTML (I didn&rsquo;t need to), but I rewrote the CSS to better fit my programming style and make it simpler to do a simple color scheme change, without having to guess at the variable names.</p>

<p>There is also a fair amount of CSS3 thrown into the mix, with a couple of transitions (namely, mouseover effects for the links), some rounded corners, and alpha-transparent backgrounds.</p>

<h3>Ruby and YAML</h3>

<p>Most of this section doesn&rsquo;t really relate to the theme itself, but since building the theme was part of the project of redoing my site, I&rsquo;m just going to include this, as well. The theme itself really only needs the HTML and CSS related stuff.</p>

<p>Since GitHub is a Ruby shop, it&rsquo;s only natural that Jekyll and, by extension, Octopress are Ruby based. I didn&rsquo;t delve a whole lot into the Ruby code, but I did use it a little to customize a couple of plugins I found (incidentally, before I found better ones), and to add a little template logic into the header section, to display things like a link to GitHub, or a &ldquo;Highlights&rdquo; page (in my case, I used the &ldquo;Highlights&rdquo; page to list all entries under the &ldquo;projects&rdquo; category). I also added a couple entries to the Gemfile to add the GSL and Classifier gems to the Bundler install script, so that I could make use of the &ldquo;related posts&rdquo; capabilities of Jekyll.</p>

<p>The configuration is all done through YAML files, which, of course, requires editing them so that things work as I want them to. This includes defining a separate set of sidebar widgets for the individual post view page vs the list view page, adding my own configuration options for the theme, and activating the &ldquo;related posts&rdquo; plugin. I also added an abbreviations plugin, which contains a list of known abbreviations and wraps any it finds in posts or pages in <code>&lt;abbr&gt;</code> tags. I&rsquo;ve added significantly to this list, so that it covers more abbreviations.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/octopress-theme-toytown">The theme is up on GitHub</a>, so feel free to fork it and play around with it. I made it largely for personal use, so I have next to no documentation for it, but I&rsquo;ve tried to make it simple enough that it should be easy to modify. It&rsquo;s also probably going to be an evolving project, as I find things I don&rsquo;t like or are broken entirely. All in all, it&rsquo;s been a fun project so far, though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anatomy of an Octopress Theme]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/16/anatomy-of-an-octopress-theme/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-16T01:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/16/anatomy-of-an-octopress-theme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you can probably see, I&rsquo;ve updated my theme to something a little less Octopress. I still have a few changes to make, such as getting a background image that fits a larger viewport. It probably also needs some polishing for things that I haven&rsquo;t run across yet, and deal with IE8 and below&rsquo;s lack of support for RGBA and media queries, and I might toy around with how it responds to different sizes (oh yeah, and tweak how lists in the content are laid out), but other than that, it&rsquo;s pretty much done.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m by no means a designer, so I doubt anyone but me will really like it, and if my history has anything to say, I probably won&rsquo;t like it myself in six months, but for the time being, at least, it&rsquo;s not the very generic, default theme. It also adds a base theme to the (currently insanely small) pool of Octopress themes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>So, What&rsquo;s the Verdict?</h2>

<p>Overall, it wasn&rsquo;t too bad. If you&rsquo;re already familiar with CSS preprocessers, such as LESS or Sass, then you&rsquo;re already well on your way to modifying the theme, Octopress uses a series of Sass files to generate the final stylesheet. Unfortunately, I take issue with a number of things with how the default theme handles things. It&rsquo;s no wonder there haven&rsquo;t been very many themes made. For such a simplistic and hacker-friendly framework, it&rsquo;s kind of a pain in the ass to theme.</p>

<h3>The Sheer Number of Files</h3>

<p>For a theme that&rsquo;s supposed to be mobile friendly and responsive, there are a <em>ton</em> of files. Granted, they all get generated and compressed down into a single, minified file, but it seems Sass and Compass don&rsquo;t merge common declarations that are split between files. This results in a lot of declaration overwriting. Fire up your favorite browser&rsquo;s developer tools, and let it display overwritten declarations, and you&rsquo;ll see what I mean.</p>

<p>All those files also means a lot of digging to find things. A lot of files had variables, mixins, and/or extension templates within them, making it difficult to track down exactly what went where (and also made it possible to break the entire thing just by changing one element). It&rsquo;s no wonder they have the &ldquo;custom&rdquo; folder. At the folder level, all these files are organized pretty well; dig deeper, and you start getting into some trouble.</p>

<h3>Context-Specific Variables (And a Ton of Them)</h3>

<p>The default theme has 11 color variables, 6 font-family variables, and 13 measurement variables, just in the &ldquo;custom&rdquo; folder (there are a dozen or so more scattered throughout the theme SCSS files), and they&rsquo;re all context-specific names, like $sidebar-link-color, $footer-bg, and $sans. This is a bit of a nightmare for maintainability and customizability, because once you change the value of, say, $serif, to a sans-serif font, you&rsquo;ve destroyed the perceived meaning of the variable.</p>

<h3>Nuke The World Resets</h3>

<p>Yes, plural. There are two resets &ndash; one named &ldquo;reset-html5&rdquo; and one named &ldquo;global-reset&rdquo;. Global-reset, in particular, is a &ldquo;nuke the world&rdquo; reset. <em>Everything</em> is reset. Headings look the same as paragraphs, it&rsquo;s chaos. For a mobile-friendly site, that&rsquo;s a lot of things to get undone, only to be redone a short time later.</p>

<p>Especially when dealing with mobile-friendly and responsive sites, I&rsquo;m a big fan of normalizing versus &ldquo;reseting&rdquo;. The reset-html5 seems to leave enough things alone, though, that I left that one. I might ultimately just use normalize.css, though.</p>

<h3>Zero Documentation for Contributors</h3>

<p>Octopress has a lot going for it, including great documentation for <em>using</em> the system (there&rsquo;s documentation <em>everywhere</em>, even in the source!), and even some for doing basic modifications to the default theme (overriding styles, changing the custom HTML in the templates, etc). However, for hackers&hellip;there&rsquo;s not much. Kind of ironic for what touts itself as &ldquo;a blogging framework for hackers&rdquo; (or, as I&rsquo;ve been inclined to call it, &ldquo;Nerdpress&rdquo;).</p>

<p>&ldquo;But real hackers don&rsquo;t use documentation!&rdquo;</p>

<p>Yeah&hellip;about that. Hackers are, at the core, problem solvers. If there&rsquo;s something we want done, we&rsquo;ll get it done. However, having documentation designed for contributors is part of being a good open source project, especially once you get large enough to <em>have</em> contributors. It saves time and headache.</p>

<p>&ldquo;But Ruby&rsquo;s a readable language!&rdquo;</p>

<p>That may be, but SCSS isn&rsquo;t so readable (granted, it&rsquo;s better than plain CSS in most cases), and the issue is compounded when things are spread across a dozen files. Additionally, in code documentation is less about <em>what</em> and more about <em>why</em> something is done a certain way.</p>

<p>That said, the &ldquo;core team&rdquo; of this project I&rsquo;m pretty sure is still one person, so given that, it&rsquo;s not surprising that there&rsquo;s a lack of documentation for developers (especially since he&rsquo;s still active on it). Hopefully, that will be only a temporary complaint as the project continues to grow and mature.</p>

<h3>The Silver Lining</h3>

<p>Now, it really isn&rsquo;t all bad. There&rsquo;s actually a nifty little system in place that it seems most people don&rsquo;t know about. In the root folder, there&rsquo;s a hidden folder called <code>.themes</code> (for you Windows folks, the dot in front of the file or folder name makes it hidden). That&rsquo;s where your themes are stored. If you&rsquo;ve installed one of the custom themes, you may have noticed that that&rsquo;s where the instructions tell you to clone their git repository to, but if you&rsquo;ve never tried installing a theme, you probably don&rsquo;t know it&rsquo;s there.</p>

<p>Additionally, the <code>rake install</code> command actually takes a parameter, of which &ldquo;classic&rdquo; is the default. This parameter allows you to tell Octopress what theme to install. Once you find out these two little tidbits, you no longer have to worry so much about your customizations getting nuked by an Octopress update.</p>

<p>As I mentioned before, it&rsquo;s also pretty logical about how the files are organized within the folders, which can make it easier to find groups of styles, even if finding specific ones are more difficult. Also, the modular approach, while not without its drawbacks, does have the advantage of allowing you to leave alone whole files (or make only slight modifications) if you want to keep certain things (such as the styles for code blocks).</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts (or TL;DR)</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a pretty good base in the framework itself for allowing others to contribute themes, but it can certainly use some polish and refinement. I look forward to watching Octopress and its community evolve.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yes, Yes, I Know]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/15/yes/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T21:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/15/yes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I know, I need to put a new theme on this thing. It&rsquo;s funny how you start seeing something everywhere once you find out about it for the first time.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not totally sure when, but I fully plan on building a new theme. I&rsquo;d like to play around with responsive design, so this should be interesting.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll also be looking into a sort of &ldquo;tag cloud&rdquo; for the sidebar, and a way to list the &ldquo;tags&rdquo; (or, as Octopress calls them, &ldquo;categories&rdquo;). I find it hard to believe that you can put categories into your posts and not be able to make use of them.</p>

<p>Oh, and your tip for the day &ndash; I never remember to use &ldquo;rake&rdquo; for doing Octopress tasks. I always want to run &ldquo;octopress [task]&rdquo;, so I added to my ~/.bashrc the line:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="nb">alias </span><span class="nv">octopress</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;rake&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>To use it right away, just run <code>source ~/.bashrc</code>. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yet Another New Home for the Blog!]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/13/yet-another-new-home-for-the-blog/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T21:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/13/yet-another-new-home-for-the-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes, I know. It seems like I&rsquo;ve changed blog platforms on an annual basis. With a little luck, this will be the last time.</p>

<h2>What Happened?</h2>

<p>In short, I became disillusioned with Blogger. It seemed like a nice platform, at first, but I soon came to find the cracks in the foundation. So, after some thought about what I <em>really</em> want/need in a blog platform, I decided to go a different direction.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Problems With Blogger (and the Other Big Platforms)</h2>

<p>Blog platforms are great for the people who don&rsquo;t know any better, but I&rsquo;m a web developer. Not only do I get the&hellip;ahem&hellip;<em>joy</em> of seeing how the sausage is made on platforms like Wordpress, where I can look at the source code itself and even have to modify it through extensions, but I also get glimpses of that process in platforms where I&rsquo;m not privy to the source code, such as Blogger.</p>

<p>One of the first problems I ran into was the HTML that Blogger outputs in posts. It seems that Blogger was written back when Geocities was still popular, and people didn&rsquo;t care about semantic HTML, and Google doesn&rsquo;t seem to care about updating it.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s very difficult to control the style of text that isn&rsquo;t inside any kind of predictable tag block. It&rsquo;s also difficult to deal with code that&rsquo;s filled with &lt;div&gt;s that are nested twelve deep.</p>

<p>The other big problem I found was the editor. I hate the standard WYSIWYG editors, in part because I spend most of my time typing in some form of code or markup. That said, wrapping everything in &lt;p&gt; tags gets tedious, so my favorite editor for blogging is one that will deal with that tedium, while allowing me to add HTML as needed.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Why not just use Wordpress? It wraps everything in &lt;p&gt; tags!&rdquo; Yeah&hellip;it does a &ldquo;wrap the world&rdquo; thing. Instead of wrapping the text as it&rsquo;s being written, or even wrapping it on save, it does it only on <em>output</em>. Dynamically, which means it&rsquo;s an extra output step, which seems unnecessary to me. Additionally (and here&rsquo;s where the &ldquo;wrap the world!&rdquo; part comes in), it doesn&rsquo;t care what it wraps. Therefore, it wraps, say, images in their own paragraphs, or even in with a neighboring paragraph. Wordpress&rsquo;s editor also drives me insane with what it does and does not allow. Even the little bit I&rsquo;ve worked with it for client projects, I&rsquo;ve wanted to throw it out a window, due to the way the content editor tries to dictate what I can and can&rsquo;t post.</p>

<p>To Blogger&rsquo;s credit, its editor doesn&rsquo;t do what Wordpress does. On the other hand, it takes the completely opposite approach &ndash; the HTML editor doesn&rsquo;t assume anything. This means that every single paragraph has to be wrapped in &lt;p&gt; tags, by hand.</p>

<p>This wouldn&rsquo;t be too big a deal, if it weren&rsquo;t for the fact that I&rsquo;ve started posting from my mobile devices, which, of course, don&rsquo;t have great keyboards for typing HTML tags. That raises writing out the tags from mildly tedius to unacceptable. It also brings me to my next problem with Blogger.</p>

<p>The mobile app isn&rsquo;t all it&rsquo;s cracked up to be. In fact, it kind of sucks. It&rsquo;s impossible to tell if it uses rich text or HTML mode. When you save a draft, it inserts HTML, but then encodes existing HTML. On a phone, there&rsquo;s also all of about three lines visible when the keyboard is active, thanks to all the chrome. In short, it&rsquo;s a mess.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m done with this crap. Time to move on to greener pastures.</p>

<h2>Enter Octopress (and Disqus)</h2>

<p>Followers of my G+ probably noticed that I voiced my issues and mind-leaks this past weekend. I enumerated the reasons for wanting a new blogging platform, which largely hasn&rsquo;t changed, except for wanting sane HTML output, and, ideally, to be able to write it in Markdown.</p>

<p>While searching, I also stumbled on an entirely different approach to writing blogs &ndash; static site generators. You see, with your typical blogs, the content is stored in a database, and is dynamically generated each time someone visits that URL. This is a terrific mechanism&hellip;for Amazon. For a blog? Not so much, if you really think about it. The content doesn&rsquo;t change <em>that</em> much, and, with the help of a tool, even the lists can be updated accordingly. Granted, for Joe Schmoe, who has a blog because his &ldquo;brother&rsquo;s kid is good with computers,&rdquo; something like Wordpress or Blogger or even Dreamwidth is good enough. For someone who lives in the world of code? I can find something better.</p>

<p>And it seems I may have.</p>

<p>I found Octopress, but didn&rsquo;t give it much stock at first. When I first found it, I was under the mistaken impression that you put the system on a server in much the same way you would with Wordpress. It also seemed like one of those blogs where you couldn&rsquo;t have comments. I wanted commenting, so I looked elsewhere.</p>

<p>Then I stumbled onto a blog that talked about migrating to Disqus and whatever their blog platform of choice ended up being. Now, I&rsquo;d seen Disqus around, and even commented using it, but never thought much of it. It&rsquo;s one of those things that you get so used to seeing that you no longer see it at all. What I found out while reading that blog was that not only could you add it to damn near anything, but you could migrate the comments, making it completely platform-agnostic. The fact that you can use the same Disqus login for any site that uses it is just icing on the cake. I was sold so quick that my Blogger blog already has it, so that I can migrate the comments over.</p>

<p>Once I did that, options opened up for blogging platforms, because then, the built in capabilities (or lack of capabilities) no longer mattered. I now have my threaded comments wherever I go. So, I ended up circling back to Octopress, thanks to finding it pretty much everywhere when searching for &ldquo;markdown blog&rdquo;. So, I dug some more into it, and the more I read about how it works, the more I liked it.</p>

<p>I found out that you don&rsquo;t actually set it up anywhere but on your working computer. It takes some command line, and the instructions are for Debian-based Linux distributions (including Ubuntu), but again, that&rsquo;s the world I live in, so no problem there. You then hook it up to a repository that&rsquo;s hosted somewhere, tell Octopress to generate everything, and upload the generated content.</p>

<p>Upload it where? Well, there are a number of places you could, but the most convenient I found was actually GitHub (factoid: it&rsquo;s named &ldquo;Octopress&rdquo;, because it runs off of GitHub&rsquo;s Jekyll static site generator, and GitHub&rsquo;s mascot is the &ldquo;Octo-cat&rdquo;). GitHub has a &ldquo;GitHub Pages&rdquo; feature that automatically renders HTML from a repository. So, what&rsquo;s uploaded to GitHub in my <a href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/shaunagordon.github.com">personal repository</a>, is actually <em>the</em> source for the rendered blog. How cool is that? Oh, and GitHub is nice and allows you to use your own domain, free of charge (because, really, it&rsquo;s stupid to charge to allow that kind of use; it&rsquo;s a setting in a text file).</p>

<h2>What Now?</h2>

<p>Over the next&hellip;well, I don&rsquo;t know how long, I&rsquo;ll be working on migrating my Blogger over. Hopefully, the export feature is sane, and I&rsquo;ll be able to easily convert the HTML to Markdown, even if it means the third party tool. Then, I&rsquo;ll move my domain information over to it. I may even just move the rest of my site over, while I&rsquo;m at it, since I&rsquo;m already planning on reworking my site&rsquo;s design to be more mobile-friendly, and it&rsquo;s static and only a couple of pages, anyway. So, until then, I&rsquo;ll use the default Octopress theme for this blog. I&rsquo;ll have to see just how GitHub deals with more complex nameserver stuff.</p>

<p>Ah, the world of web development, ain&rsquo;t it grand?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Use Pidgin and Google Apps to Chat]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/11/01/use-pidgin-and-google-apps-to-chat/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/11/01/use-pidgin-and-google-apps-to-chat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Who doesn&#8217;t use instant messenger of some form these days? Those of us from the days when there were as many chat programs as people probably have half a dozen accounts or more, or at least did at one point (who didn&#8217;t have ICQ, MSN, AIM, <i>and</i> Yahoo?). Thank goodness for unifying applications like Pidgin/Adium, Trillian, and others.</p><p>Now that some of us old chatters have grown up and created businesses (or at least business names) of our own, we may need to add our Google Apps accounts to the mix. This is a little trickier than just adding a Gmail, or other established provider, account, but thankfully, it&#8217;s not that difficult. I found, though, that start-to-finish instructions for getting set up on Pidgin were lacking, so we&#8217;ll cover them here. These instructions will work for Pidgin, and should work for Adium (the Mac port of Pidgin), though one may find the settings in slightly different places, due to convention differences across the platforms. The basic information should also work for other clients, such as Tillian, though, obviously, you&#8217;re on your own for finding were to enter everything.</p><!-- more --><h2>1. Server Settings</h2><p>Before you can even do anything in Pidgin, you need to first set up your domain to use the XMPP chat protocol and Google as the provider, and make sure that external chat is turned on in your Google Apps account. You can do this by going into the DNS management section of your web host.</p><p><b>2 things of note:</b> First, where and how you update your DNS information will depend entirely on your host. Since every host uses a different interface, detailing every single one is beyond the scope of this article. If you don&#8217;t know how to edit your DNS listings, then you&#8217;ll need to consult your host&#8217;s documentation or help system.</p><p>Second, many hosting companies offer a wizard for setting up a domain to work with Google Apps. These scripts are great for getting email and whatnot associated, but they unfortunately do not include setting up for chat. You will need to set this up manually.</p><h3>Turn on Google Chat</h3><p>This should be enabled by default, but if you&#8217;re not sure, or you turned it off previously, sign in to your Google Apps account with an administrative account and go into the domain management section.</p><p>On your dashboard, there should be a &#8220;Your Google apps&#8221; widget. If &#8220;Chat&#8221; does not show up in the list, then click on the &#8220;Enable more services link&#8221; and find the &#8220;Chat&#8221; service and make sure it&#8217;s turned on.</p><h3>Edit Your SRV Entries</h3><p>Google has a <a href="http://support.google.com/a/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=34143" target="_blank">nice little documentation page</a> that includes the information needed to fill in for your SRV entries. Specifically, you want to keep note of the data itself:</p><p>_xmpp-server._tcp.<b>yourdomain.com</b>. IN   SRV     5 0 5269 xmpp-server.l.google.com.<br />_xmpp-server._tcp.<b>yourdomain.com</b>. IN   SRV     20 0 5269 alt1.xmpp-server.l.google.com.<br />_xmpp-server._tcp.<b>yourdomain.com</b>. IN   SRV     20 0 5269 alt2.xmpp-server.l.google.com.<br />_xmpp-server._tcp.<b>yourdomain.com</b>. IN   SRV     20 0 5269 alt3.xmpp-server.l.google.com.<br />_xmpp-server._tcp.<b>yourdomain.com</b>. IN   SRV     20 0 5269 alt4.xmpp-server.l.google.com.</p><p>When filling out your SRV entries, replace <b>yourdomain.com</b> with the domain you want to use to connect to.</p><h2>2. Pidgin Settings</h2><p>This is where things aren&#8217;t quite so straightforward. As you&#8217;re probably aware, with your Gmail account (and other XMPP direct providers), you simply fill in the username and domain fields, and Pidgin happily picks up the rest of details. For your custom setup, though, there&#8217;s a little more to fill in.</p><p>First, to add your account, select &#8220;XMPP&#8221; for the provider. Set the username and domain the same way you did with your Gmail account, with the username as the portion to the left of the @ symbol in your email, and the domain as the portion to the right of it.</p><p>Since you&#8217;re piggybacking off of Google&#8217;s servers, which have a different domain name, you need to fill in the <b>resource</b> field with <i>gmail.com/</i> (yes, include the slash).</p><p>After that, go over to the &#8220;Advanced&#8221; tab and fill in the following information:</p><p><b>Connect port:</b> 5222<br /><b>Connect server:</b> talk.google.com<br /><b>File transfer proxies:</b> proxy.jabber.org</p><p>(*Note:* I&#8217;ve found that Pidgin might insist on using proxy.eu.jabber.org, this doesn&#8217;t seem to affect file transfers. I think the important part is that it&#8217;s a jabber.org address.) </p><p>Click &#8220;Save&#8221; and you&#8217;re done!</p><p>If Pidgin cannot connect, it may be due to the fact that it takes some time for DNS changes to propagate through the Internet. If you just added your SRV entries, you may need to wait a day for the changes to take full effect.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun with Python!]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/05/04/fun-with-python/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/05/04/fun-with-python</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I&#8217;m terrible about coming up with projects to do to learn a new language. As such, I generally pick them up as jobs require them. This makes it difficult to find a good reason to pick up a new language for me. So, when I made the decision earlier this week to learn Python, I decided to go a slightly different route - Gedit plugin development!</p> <!-- more --><p>So, I picked a plugin from the Gnome Gedit plugin wishlist and was going to start with it. At the time, I was using Gedit for some development (because it allowed me to edit on the remote server that I need to use for a project), but I felt it was lacking in some things that I thought would be useful (after already loading it up with plugins). That actually lead me to seeing if something was already out there. Then I remembered the <a href="https://github.com/gmate/gmate">Gmate project</a>.</p> <p>Gmate has some great plugins, but Gnome 3 is out now, and with it, Gedit 3, and a new Gedit API. This means that all the old plugins need updated to work with Gedit 3. For some reason, not all of the plugins in the Gmate package have been updated yet, so I decided against writing a new plugin from scratch and work on porting the Gmate stuff.</p> <p>And that&#8217;s what I did. I&#8217;ve so far successfully ported Gemini, a basic bracket-completion plugin, and am currently working on Find In Files. For those interested, my fork can be found <a href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/gmate">here, on Github</a>.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a Difference, Even as a Peon]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/04/02/making-difference-even-as-peon/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/04/02/making-difference-even-as-peon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>We&#8217;ve all been there &#8211; the peon, low-level, replaceable employee at the bottom of the corporate food chain. Unfortunately, since we can&#8217;t all be wildly successful business owners, or get promoted to management almost immediately, we sometimes have to do what we can in our little peon positions. It&#8217;s heartening, then, to find <a href="http://jamesshore.com/Change-Diary/">James Shore&#8217;s Change Diary</a>, via <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2006/09/changing-your-organization-for-peons.html">Jeff Atwood&#8217;s blog</a>, from when James was working as a developer shortly after the DotCom bust. </p><p>It&#8217;s a long read, and I haven&#8217;t quite gotten all the way through it, but even what I&#8217;ve read so far has made it well worth the read. There&#8217;s success, there&#8217;s failure, but most of all, there&#8217;s proof that even one peon can make a difference in a company. It&#8217;s a lesson that employees and managers alike would do well to learn, I think. </p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Fedora 16]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/02/05/review-fedora-16/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/02/05/review-fedora-16</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Those who know me know that I&#8217;m a Linux fan (and a fan of Open Source software in general), so it&#8217;s probably no surprise that I run a version of Linux on at least my personal computers. In fact, being a PHP developer lends itself very well to using Linux on my work computers, too. Previously, I used Ubuntu, a popular Debian-based version. I still would recommend Ubuntu to those looking to get their feet wet with Linux, but my own path and workflow needs took me away from it with their recent change to a user interface they call &#8220;Unity&#8221;. I found the Mac-like Unity interface to be too hostile to my dual monitor setup, and at the time, Gnome 3 on it wasn&#8217;t very stable, and I didn&#8217;t really care for the other desktop UIs that are available. Since I actually liked Gnome 3, I decided to try a distribution that has it integrated. I was already somewhat familiar with the Red Hat family of operating systems from dabbling with it back before Red Hat proper became an enterprise solution, so Fedora (often referred to as Red Hat&#8217;s testing ground) seemed like an obvious choice.</p><!-- more --><p>I started out with Fedora 15 (&#8220;Lovelock&#8221;), about two months before 16 (&#8220;Verne&#8221;) came out. While there are quite a few changes under the hood, a typical user won&#8217;t likely see much of a difference between the two versions. The average user is most likely to notice the new available wallpaper (a gorgeous homage to Fedora 16&#8217;s namesake), the new options in the user menu, and perhaps that their Gnome 3 extensions no longer work.<br /></p><h2>Gnome 3</h2><p>Gnome 3, of course, is the big thing most users will notice when they first load up Lovelock or Verne. The Fedora and Gnome teams made/chose a good theme for the Gnome Shell default. <br /></p><p>New users might find themselves faced with a bit of a learning curve as they adjust to the interface, since it&#8217;s a little different from anything but Ubuntu&#8217;s Unity. In my experience, though, it&#8217;s nice to have things like the system tray (in Windows, where programs that run in the background, such as Dropbox, minimize/close to, usually in the lower right hand side, right by the clock) disappear unless the mouse is moved over its footprint. <br /></p><p>New users will also find customization options lacking, but that&#8217;s only because the customization tool isn&#8217;t installed by default with Gnome. Gnome-Tweak-Tool is a necessity that really should be included with the default install. It provides the tools needed to even do things like add extensions, change the theme, change the system fonts, and change the window chrome behavior (how windows react to double-clicking the titlebar, the presence of the minimize, maximize, and close buttons, etc). Gnome and Fedora provide great defaults, but it&#8217;s always nice to have the ability to&#8230;well&#8230;tweak things as necessary. For those that want more than just what even Tweak Tool provides, Gnome 3&#8217;s UI runs off of CSS and scripting languages (including, but not limited to, JavaScript and Python), which means changing individual items on the theme is as simple as cracking open the CSS file, finding the entry for the object in question, and making the desired change. This only works for those that are comfortable diving into code, but for those that are, it opens up huge opportunities for extensive customization (granted, as a web developer, I&#8217;m biased).<br /></p><p>Upgrading users who previously installed extensions may notice that they&#8217;re all disabled. This is due to Verne updating to Gnome 3.2. While most of the extensions work fine when enabling them again, I found the User Theme Switcher and Alternative Shut Down extensions cause Gnome 3 to crash. A little looking provided me with a solution for Alternative Shut Down. It turns out that not having a user image selected for the user menu causes the crash. Simply click the user image in the user menu to select an image (for whatever reason that default image doesn&#8217;t work) and save the change. You can then safely enable the Alternative Shutdown Menu extension. Several months later, this solution still works wonderfully.<br /></p><p>I haven&#8217;t found a solution to the user theme switcher extension, but I haven&#8217;t really looked. I&#8217;ve so far just chalked it up to it needing an update in the Fedora repository. Since I haven&#8217;t had a desire to change the theme, and it&#8217;s still doable from Gnome Tweak Tool, I haven&#8217;t worried about it.<br /></p><p>Being an old Gnome user, and a mouse-heavy user at that, I had a little bit of a learning curve for some of Gnome&#8217;s more widely-used features, such as the quick the search-and-find of applications. Once I learned that I could open any application I wanted simply by pressing Super (Windows) to activate the overlay, then typing in the name of the program I want (or some variation thereof, as there is a certain amount of fuzzy matching), the best match is automatically highlighted, so hitting Enter opens it. This makes it significantly quicker, and less clunky, to open applications.<br /></p><p>Gnome also has a fun little feature where you simply throw your cursor up to the corner and it will open the overlay (saving you a click). This feature is nice and all&#8230;but on a dual-screen setup, this, by default, makes even the inside corner (where the two monitors meet, and there functionally isn&#8217;t a corner) activate it (at least when the Gnome activity panel is on the right hand screen). This is mildly annoying, though for me, hasn&#8217;t been enough to make me find a way to change it.<br /></p><h2>Automatic Service Starting</h2><p>This isn&#8217;t so much a difference between Lovelock and Verne as it is a difference between Ubuntu and Fedora, but for those, like me, who have switched, this can be a source of confusion. What I found was that some programs that, in Ubuntu, would be set to start automatically, don&#8217;t necessarily do the same in Fedora. Specifically, I found that both MySQL Server and Nginx did not start automatically by default. This may not be an issue for most users, since most people don&#8217;t run web and database servers on their computers, but it is something to keep in mind, and it is easily fixed with an addition to the Systemctl.<br /></p><h2>Yum vs Apt</h2><p>Another change solely from the distro move, but I think it&#8217;s worth commenting about. I&#8217;ve found I love Yum so much more than Apt. In Ubuntu, I found myself using apt-get to install and remove software, and installing Aptitude for searching and other functions, because it was easier than trying to remember &#8220;apt-cache&#8221; and the other apt-whatever tools (to me, remembering &#8220;apt-cache&#8221; was difficult, because I wouldn&#8217;t think of searching a cache to find things to install, and apt-get is what I use to install things, so why can&#8217;t it search?). Having all of the functionality in one application was quite the boon to my love of command-line-based software installation.<br /></p><p>Yum can be a little bit slower to start, initially, because it has to go through and update all of its repositories, but once that&#8217;s done, I find it very fast and powerful to use.<br /></p><h2>Miscellaneous Thoughts</h2><p>It&#8217;s actually really hard for me to write more of a review, because once I learned the keyboard shortcuts for starting applications, Gnome, and the operating system as a whole, simply stays out of my way (and I work on it upwards of 12 hours a day). It&#8217;s not uncommon for me to have 12 or more windows open, across my two monitors, and Fedora handles it all beautifully (99% of the time, any crashes are the fault of the application, and the crash is exclusive to said application). <br /></p><p>All in all, I love Fedora, and would recommend it to anyone looking to try out a version of Linux, or looking for a version of Linux that is stable and does what they want, without getting in the way.<br /></p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New home for the blog!]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/10/07/new-home-for-blog/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/10/07/new-home-for-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<h2>Why the new home?</h2><p>SilverStripe is great, but, like the rest of the platform, there&#8217;s not much to it. This isn&#8217;t bad in and of itself, I just don&#8217;t have time to essentially build and maintain the workings of a blog. So, I&#8217;ve decided to basically outsource that aspect, so that I can focus on the content of my blog, and the core of my website (which, admittedly, has been sorely neglected).</p><!-- more --><h2>Why Blogger?</h2><p>I&#8217;m a hopeless Google addict, for starters. :)</p><p>Seriously, though, while that is part of the reason (more Google accounts than I can count, multiple Android devices&#8230;), I actually put a lot of thought into where I was going to host my blog. </p><p>I am familiar with many different blogging platforms. My private blog has been on LiveJournal for nearly 10 years, though I&#8217;ve technically left it for its cousin site, Dreamwidth (I say cousin, because it&#8217;s a fork of the LiveJournal codebase), I&#8217;ve dabbled in Wordpress off and on over the years, and even had and account at HubPages for a time. They all have their pros and cons, and are all great in their own right, but Blogger had what I needed:</p><ul><li>Simple posting interface (give me a text field and I&#8217;m happy)</li><li>Option to use HTML directly</li><li>Option to monetize (I&#8217;m still debating whether I&#8217;ll actually do it, but having the option lets me make that choice)</li><li>Code highlighting*</li><li>URL customization (ability to use own)</li><li>Style customization</li><li>Free options</li><li>Hosted</li><li>Threaded comments</li></ul><p>*None of the blogging platforms that I looked at actually have this built in, but thankfully, there are now services such as Gist that allow embedding code snippets in any blog, so while I need it, it ended up a lower priority than it would have otherwise been.</p><p>Most of the platforms that I looked at have most of these options, so it pretty much came down to what had the most, and perhaps any extra goodies (such as Blogger&#8217;s mobile app, which is nifty, albeit a little rough around the edges).</p><br /></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Templates for Munin]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/04/18/jeremy-clarke-made-nice-sleek/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/04/18/jeremy-clarke-made-nice-sleek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Jeremy Clarke made a nice, sleek theme/template set for Munin (see his <a href="http://simianuprising.com/2011/02/19/raven-my-custom-theme-templates-for-munin/" target="_blank">original post</a> about it). Since, like him, I hate the default theme (it&#8217;s ugly, and done in 90s style table layout), I wanted to change it, but I currently don&#8217;t have the time to write my own theme (not that there&#8217;s much documentation on the topic, despite how awesome Munin actually is). Jeremy&#8217;s seems to be the only one on the entire Internet aside from the default and default-alt themes, and he did a great job with what he had. However, I had some issues getting it working on the version I&#8217;m running (1.4.4). It was mainly just missing files (kinda-sorta-not really his fault, Munin should probably just ignore things like missing images and allow the page to break, instead of halting copying the files to the html directory).</p><p>Anywho, so I grabbed the copy by Kim (in the comments), who was kind enough to update the theme for 1.4.* (it was originally for 1.3.*), but her copy didn&#8217;t have the required files, either. So, I got it working in my test environment and then updated the template folder with the necessary files. I&#8217;m posting it here for easy downloading.</p><p><a title="Raven theme GitHub project" href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/raven-munin-theme">Download Raven Munin theme.</a></p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project: Rock Short Vine]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/01/22/project-rock-short-vine/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/01/22/project-rock-short-vine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<ul>
    <li><b>Launched:</b> October 2010</li>
    <li><b>Status:</b> Unrecognizabily Modified (The live site may look similar to original launch, but the underlying code is no longer intact.)
</ul>
<p>This is probably one of my favorite projects that I&#8217;ve done.</p><p>I don&#8217;t think I can speak highly enough of my experience with <a title="Nick Smith creative" href="http://nicksmithcreative.com/">Nick Smith</a>. Not only did he create what I think was a phenomenal design, but he was pretty much my dream designer. This was my first project with him, but I hope I can do more.</p><!-- more --><p>One of the big things I take issue with is people treating websites like a screen-based viewer for printed media. So many people expect the exact same experience on Internet Explorer 6, or some ancient AOL browser, as on Chrome 7 or Safari 5 for Mac (I kid you not, I&#8217;ve had a client that insisted on pixel-perfect AOL 9 support). I&#8217;ll go into detail about why this isn&#8217;t a good idea in another post, but the Reader&#8217;s Digest version is that it holds back web innovation and fails to take advantage of what the Web as a medium has to offer. What I loved about working with Nick is that he was different. He understood that the Web is not print, and shouldn&#8217;t be treated as such.</p><p>Nick took this project on as a side gig in his spare time, which I think is why I only ended up with a full design for the front page, and because of that, I was able to work with him more to come up with a look for the rest of the site, and it showed how much he understood the need for slight changes in the design on my part, and a little improv from both of us.</p><p>We were under a bit of a time crunch, thanks to some breakdowns in upstream communication, so one of the things that wasn&#8217;t clear in his design was what to do with the navigation and footer when the browser window is larger than the width of the design (it was already complex enough, and most of it was single-column anyway, so I opted to make it fix-width). With the drop shadows on the navigation, especially, I found it didn&#8217;t look right keeping the red ribbon fixed-width, so I made it stretch with the screen. When I told Nick about it, he loved it and agreed that it was keeping with the <em>spirit</em> of the design.</p><p>A few days later, I was in need of a finalized design for the internal pages. Since I hadn&#8217;t heard from Nick, I decided to provide a suggestion. The asphalt background was too much for text to sit directly on it, so an intermediary background had to be put behind any content. I mentioned to him that I really liked the crumpled paper look from the logos at the bottom of the first page and thought it should be carried over to the other pages to help tie them together. I also mentioned that I had tried using the paper images I had for the Places list and that they still seemed a little too busy for regular text (though logos did fine on them), so something a little more subtle would be needed. He suggested a &#8220;hinting&#8221; technique, where the tops and bottoms of content blocks had the paper background that would then fade into a plain white background, giving the illusion of being paper. With a little CSS magic to provide both background images to each content block, the effect looked great.</p><p>Due to the time crunch, I also wasn&#8217;t able to add some effects (such as the block shadows) to Internet Explorer (IE uses proprietary filters for various CSS-like effects, and they tend to be a bit of a pain to have to continually update while in the development process, so I wait until last to minimize their changes). Therefore, the site sort of accidentally uses progressive enrichment. It&#8217;s largely subtle or minor effects, such as a radial shadow on the asphalt background, gradients and drop shadows on the top navigation ribbon, a couple slightly rotated objects, and a lowered opacity of the Bearcats logo (to make it look like it&#8217;s painted on the asphalt). None of these are really design-breaking, and certainly aren&#8217;t functionality-breaking, though it does provide users of browsers that support these CSS3 features a more appealing experience.</p><p>I also got to play pretty extensively with the Google Maps API, as well as its ability to generate custom place markers (an idea I ran with). I had a lot of fun building the list of places (pulled from a database) that linked to pins on the map, so that clicking on a list item would make the map center on the pin and open an info bubble. While this was technically a feature originally done in the O Spot webapp by my predecessor, I was using a more recent version of the Google Maps API, which included a number of code changes, requiring changes to how the API was accessed and utilized, as well as rendering the pin generator used by O Spot obsolete. So, though I was able to reuse bits and pieces of the O Spot code, I still largely needed to write new code, thus allowing me to learn how to solve that problem myself.</p><p>All in all, it was a great mix of technologies and challenges, and I had a ton of fun on this project.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[(SilverStripe) Syntax Highlighter Not Working? Try This Workaround!]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/01/11/silverstripe-syntax-highlighter-not/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/01/11/silverstripe-syntax-highlighter-not</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>So, after three days of failed code and equally failed Google searches, I finally got <a href="http://alexgorbatchev.com/SyntaxHighlighter/" target="_blank">Alex Gorbatchev&#8217;s SyntaxHighlighter</a> working with SilverStripe.</p><!-- more --><h2>The Problem</h2><p>SyntaxHighlighter comes with something like 30 styles, known as &#8220;brushes,&#8221; for highlighting consistent with different language styles. Since I work with a number of different languages, I wanted to have them available to use, but not load them all on every page. The recent versions have an autoloader feature, which is awesome, and worked great&#8230;on my development server. My production server? Not so much. In fact, for some reason, I kept getting the error &#8220;Could not find brush for: [insert requested language here]&#8221;, even though I could link to it just fine.</p><p>I didn&#8217;t have the patience to figure out what was wrong (the whole &#8220;shoemaker&#8217;s kids go barefoot&#8221; thing), but my guess is that it has something to do with something on Apache and rewriting (my dev server is Nginx, which I&#8217;ve grown to love thanks to my latest client, while the production server is Apache with a cPanel front). Instead, I decided to make a workaround.</p><h2>The Solution</h2><p>Perhaps, I&#8217;m a carpenter with only a hammer in this situation, so I see this as a nail, even if it really isn&#8217;t, but I decided to solve the problem The PHP Way&trade;.</p><p>First, of course, download SyntaxHighlighter and unzip it into the root of your SilverStripe install (I just named its root folder &#8220;sh&#8221; for easy coding). Don&#8217;t forget to pick up the <a title="SyntaxHL TinyMCE plugin" href="https://github.com/RichGuk/syntaxhl" target="_blank">SyntaxHL TinyMCE plugin</a> for the HTML Editor and install it (in SilverStripe 2.4.4, copy the extracted files into /sapphire/thirdparty/tinymce/plugins/), so you can have a convenient button in which to add your code.</p><p>Now, let&#8217;s get down to the fun!</p><p>The first thing we need to do is add a field into the CMS so we can list what brushes we want to use when we use SyntaxHighlighter on a page, so in the model for the page type you&#8217;re adding brushes to, put the following:</p><pre class="brush: php;fontsize: 100; first-line: 1; highlight: [3]; ">function getCMSfields(){<br />    $fields = parent::getCMSfields();<br />    $fields-&gt;addFieldToTab('Root.Content.Main', new TextField('Brushes'));<br /><br />    return $fields;<br />}</pre><p>If you already have the getCMSfields() function in your model, simply add the highlighted line.</p><p>Since this was more or less a quick-and-dirty solution, and I&#8217;m the only one using my CMS, all I did was add a basic text field to the bottom of my main content page, where I&#8217;d add a comma-separated list of the brushes I want to use. If you need to ensure consistency, or want to control what brushes are available to the user, you could make the text field another type of field, such as a set of checkboxes.</p><p>In the controller for the page type you want to add your brushes to, create a function to provide the array that view will use:</p><pre class="brush: php;fontsize: 100; first-line: 1; ">function Brushes() {<br />        $BrushSet = new DataObjectSet();<br />        $shBrushes = explode(',', $this-&gt;Brushes);<br /><br />        foreach ($shBrushes as $brush) {<br />            $BrushSet-&gt;push(new ArrayData(array(<br />                        'Brush' =&gt; ucwords($brush)<br />                    )));<br />        }<br /><br />        return $BrushSet;<br />    }</pre><p>The controller function simply takes the comma-separated string, creates an array, then puts it into the DataObjectSet for outputting into the view. The ucwords() call ensures that each item is capitalized, following the files&#8217; naming structure.</p><p>Now, on to the view!</p><p>First, we need to add the base files to make SyntaxHighlighter work. I&#8217;ve added the Django theme, since it matches my site&#8217;s color scheme as of this writing (and I just like it). SyntaxHighlighter comes with a number of themes, so just load what you want after the shCore.css file for the color scheme. After that, add the core JavaScript file. I use the regular syntax for the JavaScript files so that I can add them where I want (the template syntax, by default, automatically puts them at the bottom of the document, either above the closing body tag, or above any existing script tags; I&#8217;ve found that this will keep some scripts from working), and put the core file in the document head. Below that is the custom control for the script tag that will load the individual brushes. Finally, the shLoad file, which applies the brushes to the tags that call for them.</p><pre class="brush: xml;fontsize: 100; first-line: 1; "><pre class="brush: xml;fontsize: 100; first-line: 1; ">&lt;% require css(sh/styles/shCore.css) %&gt;<br />&lt;% require css(sh/styles/shThemeDjango.css) %&gt;<br />&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://ShaunaGordon.com/sh/scripts/shCore.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;<br /><br />&lt;% control Brushes %&gt;<br />    &lt;% include Brush %&gt;<br />&lt;% end_control %&gt;<br /><br />&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://ShaunaGordon.com/sh/shLoad.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</pre></pre><p>Finally, we need to create the include file for our Brush control. This is simply the following script call:</p><pre class="brush: xml;fontsize: 100; first-line: 1; ">&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://ShaunaGordon.com/sh/scripts/shBrush{$Brush}.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</pre><p>Note the {$Brush} variable in the tag. Conveniently, the brushes are named according to a standard, with the last segment being the language the brush is for. The only caveat this means for our setup is that we have to remember the names the files use. This could be remedied by using a system that generates the options, though doing that would require going into the code again if you add new brushes (either adding to the files or adding more choices to your list). Such is the trade-off to be considered, based on your circumstances.</p><p>Don&#8217;t forget to add the button to your editor, in your mysite/_config.php file, add the lines:</p><pre class="brush: php;fontsize: 100; first-line: 1; ">// SyntaxHighlighter TinyMCE Plugin<br />HtmlEditorConfig::get('cms')-&gt;enablePlugins('syntaxhl');<br />HtmlEditorConfig::get('cms')-&gt;insertButtonsAfter('charmap', 'syntaxhl');</pre><p>I added the button after the Specials Character map, since it&#8217;s at the end of the formatting row, but it can really be added anywhere. You just need to know the name of the button you want to put it after.</p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>And there you have it. A quick /dev/build and you should be up and running with syntax highlighting, The PHP Way&trade;!</p><p>The AuthoLoader is probably a better way of doing it, if you can (because it calls the brushes automatically when you request them), but this should provide a nice workaround if you find yourself in my situation and can&#8217;t seem to get the AutoLoader working properly.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Little on 1099 Contract Employees]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2010/08/08/little-on-1099-contract-employees/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2010/08/08/little-on-1099-contract-employees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Currently, here in Columbus, the trend in employing web developers is to hire independent contractors. In many cases, they&#8217;re &#8220;contract to hire,&#8221; where the idea is that the employee would work on a contract basis for the first couple of months, then be hired for full benefits after this &#8220;trial period.&#8221; In some of those cases, that &#8220;trial&#8221; period never actually ends, and the employee is expected to show up to work every day and not receive the full benefits of employment. This practice, however, isn&#8217;t necessary legal. Whether you&#8217;re a contractor or an employer, you should know where that line is between contractor and employee.</p><!-- more --><h2>The Law</h2><p>The IRS has a law that details particular qualifications that determine whether a person is an employee or independent contractor. According to <a title="Findlaw - Employee or Contractor?" href="http://library.findlaw.com/2000/Feb/1/127759.html">Findlaw</a>, there are twenty factors that determine whether a person is an employee or an independent contractor.</p><p>These factors include:</p><ul><li>Level of Instruction</li><li>Training</li><li>Degree of business integration</li><li>Extent of personal services</li><li>Continuity of relationship</li><li>Flexibility of schedule</li><li>Demands for full-time work</li><li>Need for on-site services</li><li>Sequence of work</li><li>Requirements for reports</li><li>Method of payment</li><li>Payment of business or travel expenses</li><li>Provision of tools and materials</li><li>Investment in facilities</li><li>Realization of profit or loss</li><li>Work for multiple companies</li><li>Availablity to the public</li><li>Control over discharge</li><li>Right of termination</li></ul><p>These factors are considered on a whole, with some factors holding more weight than others, to determine whether a person is a contractor or an employee. Utimately, it comes down to who has control over when, where, and how a person&#8217;s work is done. If the employer has most or all of the control, then the worker is a de facto employee. If not, then the worker is an independent contractor.</p><h2>The Implications</h2><p>What this law means is that employers should be careful about how they use their contractors. Likewise, workers should be aware of what their rights are. If the IRS gets involved and reclassifies contract workers as employees, employers owe the IRS the back taxes for the length of time determined, and then have to provide the workers with the benefits of employees if the company continues to use their services.</p><p>Microsoft learned this the hard way in the late 1980s. They had hired a large number of &#8220;independent contractors&#8221; that were assimilated into the teams, were required to work at the offices during the company&#8217;s hours, and used the company&#8217;s equipment. The IRS determined that the &#8220;freelancers&#8221; were actually employees, and Microsoft paid the back taxes for the previous two years of the workers&#8217; employment.</p><h2>Contractors</h2><p>If you&#8217;re a contractor, keep an eye on what your employer is asking you to do, particularly if you have an ongoing relationship with them. Your ability to work for multiple, even competing companies, as well as your ability to choose when and where to work, are some of the heavier-weighted factors in whether or not you&#8217;re a de facto employee.</p><p>Be nice to your employer, particularly if the company isn&#8217;t a behemoth like Microsoft or Nationwide Insurance (another company that got in trouble with de facto employees). The law is somewhat obscure to those that aren&#8217;t lawyers, and can be hard to find within the labyrinth of federal statutes, so it&#8217;s entirely possible that a smaller company, which generally lacks an on-staff lawyer to guide their decisions, simply might not know about the law. If that&#8217;s the case, it would likely be easier to swallow the recommendation for change if it came from a worker, than if it came from the IRS and with a mandate to pay back taxes for the contractors.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
