<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: review | Shauna Gordon]]></title>
  <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-31T02:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shauna Gordon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lodging With AirBnb]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/05/19/airbnb-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T13:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/05/19/airbnb-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I had the pleasure of going to New York City for <a href="https://conference.laravel.com/">Laracon US</a>. It was a phenomenal experience, but there was one problem &mdash; New York City is bloody expensive. At $250 a night for the group rate, the hotel was no exception, and the disadvantage of being a female in a male-dominated industry is that finding a roommate to share a room with is damn near impossible. So, I was on my own for finding a way to save a little money on lodging. Unfortunately, the traditional booking agencies didn&rsquo;t really have anything that were much of a savings and near to the conference venue.</p>

<h2>Enter AirBnb</h2>

<p>Some of the guys who were involved with last year&rsquo;s Laracon EU introduced me to <a href="https://www.airbnb.com/">AirBnb</a>. It&rsquo;s an interesting concept &mdash; people rent out a room in their home for a given price per night. Generally, this results in a cost savings for the guest, and helps defray the host&rsquo;s cost of their home. AirBnb works like a booking agency, helping guests find and book places to stay; an escrow service, holding the money in the event a refund is needed and ensuring the host gets paid for services rendered; and housekeeping, making sure the room is ready for the guest and in good shape between guests.</p>

<p>I decided to check it out to see what I could find, and I lucked into an opening just <a href="https://www.airbnb.com/rooms/1851350">a couple of blocks away,</a> for about a third of the cost of a stay at the hotel. So, I put in a booking request (hosts can approve or refuse booking requests), and a short while later, my request was approved.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Pre-Flight</h2>

<p>A few days before I was to be in NYC, both AirBnb, and my host, sent a couple of emails that included pertinent information, including how to get to the apartment, how to get into the building, which bedroom to use, and how to open the murphy bed in guest room, as well as a general reminder of the trip itself. To help maintain privacy, details like the exact address are left out until after the booking is confirmed, hence the emails.</p>

<h2>Showtime</h2>

<p>Getting to the apartment was pretty easy. It had been a while, but I&rsquo;ve had some experience with NYC&rsquo;s mass transit system (the Metro Transit Authority, or MTA), so the first thing I did was find an MTA kiosk and pick up a card, then made a beeline to the bus station from LaGuardia Airport (LGA). From there, it was an easy train ride down to Soho, and a short walk to the apartment. It took about an hour to get there, which is, from what I can tell, a pretty average time between LGA and Manhattan.</p>

<p>When I got there, I followed the instructions to get in, and got into the building pretty easily&hellip;to find that his wasn&rsquo;t the only apartment, and it turned out to be a multi-story walk-up. No problem (on review of the description, that was noted, but it seems that the listing changed since I booked, so either I missed it, or it wasn&rsquo;t there before). Not an uncommon occurrence in Manhattan buildings. It&rsquo;s definitely an older building, with narrow, steep stairs indicative of 19th century (or so) architecture. As a young, decently fit adult, I didn&rsquo;t mind, but it is something to consider/ask about if one has any kind of issues that would make such a setup an issue.</p>

<p>The apartment itself was a pleasant contrast to the stairwell. It was still small and narrow, but it had been recently updated, making it a fairly attractive place to stay. I was told that the guest bedroom (which was teal in color) was &ldquo;to the left.&rdquo; Well, technically, it was more like &ldquo;around the corner,&rdquo; but it&rsquo;s not like a 500sqft apartment is easy to get lost in, and the one other bedroom was very much not teal.</p>

<p>So, I go over to the other door and&hellip;it&rsquo;s locked. Odd, but it&rsquo;s one of those locks that&rsquo;s unlocked by a coin. I find one and go in to find stuff in it. It looks like someone else is staying there. Again, this seems odd. There was never any mention made that I wasn&rsquo;t the only guest (I was under the impression that the host was renting out his spare room, and therefore would be occupying his bedroom). So, I pinged him via email, stashed my stuff, and went on my way as I was meeting with others.</p>

<p>A short while later, he emailed me that yes, indeed, there was another guest there, and I was to actually have the not-teal bedroom. As it turned out, the host wasn&rsquo;t in town at all and was renting out both rooms that week. That would have been nice to know, but really, it&rsquo;s my only real complaint, and it was straightened out with a couple of emails. Besides, it worked out largely in my favor, because I got a real bed, and not a murphy bed. Since I was using the place solely as a crash pad, and would be spending my waking hours elsewhere, the fact that I was sharing the common areas with someone else was a non-issue, and the bed was the most important feature for me.</p>

<p>From what I could tell, the murphy bed in the teal bedroom was a full bed, with a small couch for extra sleeping if needed. Not a ton of space, but enough to sleep a couple of people pretty comfortably, with some space for luggage. The other bedroom was large enough to fit a queen bed and some typical bedroom furniture, which noticeably more walking space, making it the roomier of the two rooms. A couple of large windows allow quite a bit of natural light in &mdash; which is great except for the part where it wakes the light sleeper early in the morning (actually, not a terrible thing, as it served as a great alarm clock for me to be up in time to have a leisurely breakfast with my friends before the conference started for the day; I&rsquo;ll take <em>it</em> over a blaring alarm clock). They did also let sound in pretty easily, and since it&rsquo;s in the middle of downtown Manhattan, that means the usual city sounds. Those who are used to rural areas may have a hard time sleeping, but coming from a not-so-quiet city, myself, along with long days on the town and walking everywhere made it a non-issue for me.</p>

<p>Like the apartment as a whole, the bathroom was <em>really</em> small. Now, I&rsquo;m used to small bathrooms. The combined floor space of my three bathrooms is all of 80 square feet (I can floor the largest one with a single box of flooring). But this one made even mine look large. If you&rsquo;re a large person, expect to have to step into the tub to be able to close the door, because it opens inward, and there&rsquo;s only enough floor space for the door to clear the toilet and sink, and for one&rsquo;s knees when sitting on the toilet. It&rsquo;s a tight fit, to say the least. Works for me, though, because it leaves more space for more important rooms &mdash; in this case, bedrooms. I do kind of feel bad for the other guest, as the teal bedroom was right next to the bathroom, so I doubt my early morning showers were all that welcome. At least the front door was away from that bedroom, so they weren&rsquo;t as likely to be disturbed by my coming in at all hours of the night. No doubt they wondered whether I got any amount of sleep at all, or if I was just a suitcase that showed up randomly and disappeared just as randomly.</p>

<h3>Overall Thoughts</h3>

<p>All in all, it was a good experience, and largely went as expected &mdash; I rented a bedroom in which I could crash for a couple of hours a night for a few nights. The host was great and readily responded to my questions. The location was about as perfect as I could get for my needs. The bed was comfortable and the apartment was clean. If you&rsquo;re looking to stay in New York City, I definitely recommend checking out AirBnb in general, and this Soho apartment, specifically.</p>

<p>(P.S. &mdash; If you want to use AirBnb, either for booking or for hosting, <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/sgordon52">have a referral link</a> for a $25USD credit toward your next reservation on AirBnb.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Fedora 16]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/02/05/review-fedora-16/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/02/05/review-fedora-16</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Those who know me know that I'm a Linux fan (and a fan of Open Source software in general), so it's probably no surprise that I run a version of Linux on at least my personal computers. In fact, being a PHP developer lends itself very well to using Linux on my work computers, too. Previously, I used Ubuntu, a popular Debian-based version. I still would recommend Ubuntu to those looking to get their feet wet with Linux, but my own path and workflow needs took me away from it with their recent change to a user interface they call "Unity". I found the Mac-like Unity interface to be too hostile to my dual monitor setup, and at the time, Gnome 3 on it wasn't very stable, and I didn't really care for the other desktop UIs that are available. Since I actually liked Gnome 3, I decided to try a distribution that has it integrated. I was already somewhat familiar with the Red Hat family of operating systems from dabbling with it back before Red Hat proper became an enterprise solution, so Fedora (often referred to as Red Hat's testing ground) seemed like an obvious choice.</p><!-- more --><p>I started out with Fedora 15 ("Lovelock"), about two months before 16 ("Verne") came out. While there are quite a few changes under the hood, a typical user won't likely see much of a difference between the two versions. The average user is most likely to notice the new available wallpaper (a gorgeous homage to Fedora 16's namesake), the new options in the user menu, and perhaps that their Gnome 3 extensions no longer work.<br /></p><h2>Gnome 3</h2><p>Gnome 3, of course, is the big thing most users will notice when they first load up Lovelock or Verne. The Fedora and Gnome teams made/chose a good theme for the Gnome Shell default. <br /></p><p>New users might find themselves faced with a bit of a learning curve as they adjust to the interface, since it's a little different from anything but Ubuntu's Unity. In my experience, though, it's nice to have things like the system tray (in Windows, where programs that run in the background, such as Dropbox, minimize/close to, usually in the lower right hand side, right by the clock) disappear unless the mouse is moved over its footprint. <br /></p><p>New users will also find customization options lacking, but that's only because the customization tool isn't installed by default with Gnome. Gnome-Tweak-Tool is a necessity that really should be included with the default install. It provides the tools needed to even do things like add extensions, change the theme, change the system fonts, and change the window chrome behavior (how windows react to double-clicking the titlebar, the presence of the minimize, maximize, and close buttons, etc). Gnome and Fedora provide great defaults, but it's always nice to have the ability to...well...tweak things as necessary. For those that want more than just what even Tweak Tool provides, Gnome 3's UI runs off of CSS and scripting languages (including, but not limited to, JavaScript and Python), which means changing individual items on the theme is as simple as cracking open the CSS file, finding the entry for the object in question, and making the desired change. This only works for those that are comfortable diving into code, but for those that are, it opens up huge opportunities for extensive customization (granted, as a web developer, I'm biased).<br /></p><p>Upgrading users who previously installed extensions may notice that they're all disabled. This is due to Verne updating to Gnome 3.2. While most of the extensions work fine when enabling them again, I found the User Theme Switcher and Alternative Shut Down extensions cause Gnome 3 to crash. A little looking provided me with a solution for Alternative Shut Down. It turns out that not having a user image selected for the user menu causes the crash. Simply click the user image in the user menu to select an image (for whatever reason that default image doesn't work) and save the change. You can then safely enable the Alternative Shutdown Menu extension. Several months later, this solution still works wonderfully.<br /></p><p>I haven't found a solution to the user theme switcher extension, but I haven't really looked. I've so far just chalked it up to it needing an update in the Fedora repository. Since I haven't had a desire to change the theme, and it's still doable from Gnome Tweak Tool, I haven't worried about it.<br /></p><p>Being an old Gnome user, and a mouse-heavy user at that, I had a little bit of a learning curve for some of Gnome's more widely-used features, such as the quick the search-and-find of applications. Once I learned that I could open any application I wanted simply by pressing Super (Windows) to activate the overlay, then typing in the name of the program I want (or some variation thereof, as there is a certain amount of fuzzy matching), the best match is automatically highlighted, so hitting Enter opens it. This makes it significantly quicker, and less clunky, to open applications.<br /></p><p>Gnome also has a fun little feature where you simply throw your cursor up to the corner and it will open the overlay (saving you a click). This feature is nice and all...but on a dual-screen setup, this, by default, makes even the inside corner (where the two monitors meet, and there functionally isn't a corner) activate it (at least when the Gnome activity panel is on the right hand screen). This is mildly annoying, though for me, hasn't been enough to make me find a way to change it.<br /></p><h2>Automatic Service Starting</h2><p>This isn't so much a difference between Lovelock and Verne as it is a difference between Ubuntu and Fedora, but for those, like me, who have switched, this can be a source of confusion. What I found was that some programs that, in Ubuntu, would be set to start automatically, don't necessarily do the same in Fedora. Specifically, I found that both MySQL Server and Nginx did not start automatically by default. This may not be an issue for most users, since most people don't run web and database servers on their computers, but it is something to keep in mind, and it is easily fixed with an addition to the Systemctl.<br /></p><h2>Yum vs Apt</h2><p>Another change solely from the distro move, but I think it's worth commenting about. I've found I love Yum so much more than Apt. In Ubuntu, I found myself using apt-get to install and remove software, and installing Aptitude for searching and other functions, because it was easier than trying to remember "apt-cache" and the other apt-whatever tools (to me, remembering "apt-cache" was difficult, because I wouldn't think of searching a cache to find things to install, and apt-get is what I use to install things, so why can't it search?). Having all of the functionality in one application was quite the boon to my love of command-line-based software installation.<br /></p><p>Yum can be a little bit slower to start, initially, because it has to go through and update all of its repositories, but once that's done, I find it very fast and powerful to use.<br /></p><h2>Miscellaneous Thoughts</h2><p>It's actually really hard for me to write more of a review, because once I learned the keyboard shortcuts for starting applications, Gnome, and the operating system as a whole, simply stays out of my way (and I work on it upwards of 12 hours a day). It's not uncommon for me to have 12 or more windows open, across my two monitors, and Fedora handles it all beautifully (99% of the time, any crashes are the fault of the application, and the crash is exclusive to said application). <br /></p><p>All in all, I love Fedora, and would recommend it to anyone looking to try out a version of Linux, or looking for a version of Linux that is stable and does what they want, without getting in the way.<br /></p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Handcrafted CSS]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2010/06/21/review-handcrafted-css/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2010/06/21/review-handcrafted-css</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321658531?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=graywolfweb-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0321658531">Handcrafted CSS: More Bulletproof Web Design, Video Edition</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=graywolfweb-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0321658531" width="1" height="1" /></p><p>While at one of my previous clients, a coworker ordered this book as a resource at the office. I was the first to read it and simply couldn't put it down. <em>Handcrafted CSS: More Bulletproof Web Design</em> highlights modern CSS techniques that help build robust, attractive, designs.</p><!-- more --><p>Unlike most technical books, which often provide too much tech and not enough explanation, or too much theory and not enough tech, this book provides a fantastic balance, and even uses a running case study that it builds and enhances as the reader progresses through the book. Not only are readers able to understand the concepts the book presents, but they also learn ways to put the new concepts into practice.</p><p>One of the important points the book emphasizes is <em>progressive enrichment</em>, or designing for the future. CSS3 is complete enough that some of its features can already be used in modern browsers, which already provides us with a way to create beautiful designs that don't require much, if any (let alone extensive) use of images or JavaScript -- nearly everything can be done entirely in CSS. The principles of progressive enrichment put forth in the book allow developers to write forward-thinking code, creating designs that will essentially self-improve as browsers implement more CSS capabilities.</p><p>Another unique aspect to the book is that not only can it be easily read cover-to-cover without being too dry and code-saturated, but it also serves very well as a desktop reference. The chapters and sections are organized in an easy-to-access manner and cover, in fair depth, specific features of CSS (as opposed to more broad subjects encompassing several features).</p><p>This book is a must-have for intermediate to advanced CSS coders, be they designers or developers, and even beginning coders that are serious in learning how to write robust, forward-thinking, and semantic code.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Why Work Sucks (And How to Fix It)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2010/05/16/review-why-work-sucks-and-how-to-fix-it/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2010/05/16/review-why-work-sucks-and-how-to-fix-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001OMHV0K?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=graywolfweb-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B001OMHV0K">Why Work Sucks and How to Fix It: No Schedules, No Meetings, No Joke--the Simple Change That Can Make Your Job Terrific</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=graywolfweb-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B001OMHV0K" width="1" height="1" /></p><p>You anxiously look at your watch as the traffic creeps forward - 8:55am. There's no way you'll get to the office by 9, you still have 10 miles to go. When you finally do arrive at 9:15, you try to sneak to your desk unnoticed, but your boss is already there. "So nice of you to join us this morning," he greets you, a "do it again and you're fired" look on his face. You sit down at your desk, still a little too agitated to start work quite yet, so you read your favorite news site for ten minutes. Part of you resigns to this life, believing it's the way things are, and nothing will change, but another part of you feels that there must be a better way.</p><!-- more --><p>That second part is right. There is a better way.</p><p>Former Best Buy employees Cali Ressler and Jody Thompson (now owners of <a href="http://gorowe.com">CultureRx</a>) share their experience of transforming Best Buy's corporate culture from the traditional clock-watching to a Results-Only Work Environment, or ROWE, and how ROWE can work for other companies.  The idea seems counterintuitive, at first, especially to those entrenched in traditional corporate culture and politics, but as Cali and Jody start breaking down the obstacles and overcoming objections, the idea starts to make sense. Give people control over their time, allow them to work when and where they're most productive, and grade them on their results, and instead of slacking and decreased productivity, they'll reward the company with increased performance, increased satisfaction, and lower voluntary turnover.</p><p>Why is it that the results seem counter to what managers fear? Because it's what everyone already does...just not at work. When we do our household work, we don't deal with politics, we don't "look like" we're doing something, we <em>are</em> doing things. We "grade" ourselves on whether the work gets done or not. The laundry either gets washed or put away, or it doesn't. The dishes make it into the dishwasher or they don't. We do all this stuff on the weekends or after work and don't really think about it, nor do we really get burnt out from doing the usual "home-life" stuff we need to do on a regular basis, and we can do this because we have control over our time, so we can use it as we see fit. This doesn't happen at work, because at work, we're not in control of our time. If we get done with our work without filling up our required 40 hours, then we either have to find more work to do, or we have to look busy. Going home and enjoying the rest of the day or week is out of the question.</p><p><em>Why Work Sucks</em> goes into detail about this problem, known as <a href="http://www.businessknowhow.com/manage/presenteeism.htm">presenteeism</a>, and how costly it is to companies. When an employee has a set amount of work and has to fill a 40-hour week with it, there's no incentive to work efficiently beyond keeping it from taking more than 40 hours (and even that upper limit is questionable).  The book also addresses the underhanded comments, such as "nice of you to join us," which it calls "Sludge." It explains that while on the surface and on an individual basis, these comments seem harmless, but not only do they add up, they are also designed to keep us "in line" with the corporate culture of clock watching.</p><p>Think about it, how often have you or someone you know called in sick, just so you didn't have to explain to your boss about the accident on your primary route? Or how about making a "socially acceptable" excuse because you had a hard time sleeping the night before and didn't want to get out of bed? Or any other number of stories you've lined up to tell your boss or coworkers for whatever reason why you were late coming in or early to leave or didn't make it in at all? How often have you feared that you'd be looked down on even if your real reason <em>is</em> a "socially acceptable" reason for missing or shortening your day? How many times have you come into work sick, or felt guilty about staying home when sick? These are all a result of Sludge and the corporate clock-watching culture.</p><p>ROWE, however, asks "why does the clock matter so much? The work itself is what matters," and that's the basis for ROWE &mdash; it doesn't matter how, when, or where the work gets done, as long as it <em>gets done</em> (assuming, of course, the means are legal and the work is done before any applicable deadlines). Does it really matter if Sally chooses to do her work in a coffee shop from 5pm to 2am, or that Dave does his from 6am to 11am at home, then some more from 3pm to 6pm at the park? If the work is getting done and is up to standards, then the answer is simple, it <em>doesn't</em> matter.</p><p>One of the best parts about the ROWE concept is that it's not just theory, it's in practice in Fortune 500 and Fortune 100 companies, as well as others. ROWE is already working for these companies, and these success stories provide leverage for implementing the system in even more companies. Taking a more creative look at the concept, on an individual level, working in a ROWE is not unlike working as a freelancer, except that a ROWE employee has the stability of an established company.</p><p>In all, <em>Work Sucks</em> is a must-read for anyone who knows that there must be a better way, as well as those who feel that the way things are is good enough (in other words, everyone in any kind of corporate environment). Even if your company can't fully implement a true ROWE, it can probably make use of a lot of the advice it offers.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
