<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community contribution | Shauna Gordon]]></title>
  <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/categories/community-contribution/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-31T02:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shauna Gordon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways To Keep Going (When You're Going Through Hell)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/10/30/motivation/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T22:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/10/30/motivation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When in the throes of a depressive episode (or on the edge of an anxiety attack or any other such motivation killer), it can be hard to maintain motivation and productivity. This can be detrimental when other people rely on you, or when you have a job to hold down.</p>

<p>Over the years, I&rsquo;ve found a number of things that have helped keep me motivated through low times, and have decided to share them. Unlike other articles giving advice on &ldquo;cheering up,&rdquo; the items here may or may not actually lift your mood. That&rsquo;s not the point of them, and anyone who&rsquo;s dealt with depression will tell you that most of the time, things designed to &ldquo;cheer you up&rdquo; don&rsquo;t really work. If it does lift your mood, then that&rsquo;s a positive side effect, but as Winston Churchill put it, &ldquo;when you&rsquo;re going through hell, keep going.&rdquo; These items are intended to do <em>that</em> &mdash; help you keep going.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Eat&hellip;</h2>

<p>Dysfunctional mental states, be it depression or mania, tend to screw with our eating patterns. It&rsquo;s important during these times more than ever to make sure we keep good habits.</p>

<h3>&hellip;The Right Amount</h3>

<p>Depression, especially, does one of two things to the appetite. It either kills it, or makes the person want to eat everything. For various other reasons, other mental illnesses often have similar effects. Both of these things have their own problems.</p>

<p>Eating too much food, especially the usual comfort foods of sugars and refined carbohydrates, is bad for the obvious reason that it will likely lead to weight gain, especially if it happens on a regular basis. Weight gain itself is often a self-esteem killer, and can result in a negative feedback loop, which most people already know.</p>

<p>However, the obvious &ldquo;too much food, not enough movement&rdquo; aside, dysfunctional eating can have more short-term effects on your mood and motivation, especially if you swing the other way and don&rsquo;t eat enough. By not eating enough, you deprive your body of the energy it needs to keep you going. This can start slowing you down as your body tries to conserve energy for vital uses. This state of lethargy can bring the mood down, as well as keep you from being motivated to do things. Again, a feedback loop ensues.</p>

<h3>&hellip;At Regular Intervals</h3>

<p>Like making sure to eat enough, eating at regular intervals is also important, I&rsquo;ve found. I&rsquo;m not a fan of the whole &ldquo;eat six small meals&rdquo; thing, but going half a day without food? Not necessarily a good idea. Even if you don&rsquo;t feel terribly hungry, it&rsquo;s a good idea to eat at least a little bit of food, or eat once you get hungry, even if it&rsquo;s starting to get close to the next meal time. I&rsquo;ve personally found that both my motivation and my mood start going down the farther apart my meals are. So, try to keep your regular eating schedule.</p>

<h3>&hellip;Wholesome, Whole Foods&hellip;</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found that my overall mood and motivation have largely stabilized (and at a higher base level) since switching to a whole foods-based diet. The better I eat, the less of a rollercoaster I have going on in my head.</p>

<p>A lot of the diseases of civilization can be traced back to malnourishment, at least in part. Yeah, we have no shortage of food in our Western society, but look at the quality of the vast majority of it. Frankly, it sucks, and is largely devoid of nutrients. Get back to the basics &mdash; meat, fruits, vegetables, etc. &mdash; and odds are very good that you&rsquo;ll start to see major improvements in all areas of your physical health, as your vitamin stores start actually filling back up. <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2738337/">Deficiencies in things like folate, B-12, and magnesium</a> can do a number on the brain and exacerbate depression, schizophrenia, and anxiety, among others. Eating whole foods provides your body with the most bioavailable forms of these nutrients.</p>

<h4>&hellip;Including Healthy Fats</h4>

<p>I am a big fan of the low carb, high fat (LCHF) way of eating. The ketogenic diet (an &ldquo;extreme&rdquo; form of LCHF, where fat intake is upwards of 80-90% of total calories) was originally created for epilepsy, but has <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3321471/">since been studied (or slated for study) for other neurological issues, including such things as depression, migraines, and more.</a> I had switched to it for other reasons, but found positive effects in this area, as well.</p>

<p>One of the big things that a LCHF diet teaches you is that the conventional wisdom that has been burned into our brains is wrong (which is now starting to come back to mainstream media). Where conventional wisdom lauds polyunsaturated fats and vilifies saturated fats, LCHF shows how important naturally occurring saturated fats really are, and that polyunsaturated fats should be consumed only in moderation (and certainly not in the heavily-refined, Omega-6-heavy oils that conventional wisdom have on a pedestal). So, when I say &ldquo;include healthy fats,&rdquo; I also mean saturated fats, as well as monounsaturated fats, and, more sparingly, polyunsaturated fats. The only fat to really avoid is trans fat.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t have to switch to a LCHF diet to benefit from including good fats, but a good grass-fed butter and some virgin coconut oil are manna from the gods, let me tell you.</p>

<p>(I&rsquo;m not going to go into all the nitty-gritty details of the research regarding fat in this post, or even on this blog. I have a more health/fitness/diet related blog and will write about it in the future. When that happens, I&rsquo;ll link to it for the research details. In the meantime, I welcome you to check out the recent <a href="http://annals.org/article.aspx?articleid=1846638&amp;resultClick=3">meta-analysis of a few dozen studies regarding saturated fats and heart disease</a>, and <a href="http://vimeo.com/45485034">Dr. Peter Attia&rsquo;s talk on the history of the anti-fat conventional wisdom</a>.)</p>

<h2>Do An Intense Workout At Least Once A Week</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s just something about doing something so intense that you can&rsquo;t help but focus on it and be in the moment, and, after you&rsquo;re done, want little more than a hot shower and comfy bed, that helps relieve the latent, low-level anxiety and stress that seems to kill productivity. I&rsquo;ve found that I&rsquo;m a giant ball of nerves by Wednesday afternoon, but after my evening boxing class, it&rsquo;s like night and day, and that carries me through the remainder of the week.</p>

<p>The important thing for this is to find something that forces you to focus on the moment, and wear you out. Things like martial arts or cardio boxing/kickboxing are good options, because you have to concentrate on your form, posture, moves, etc. Some martial arts also teach you various meditation/focusing techniques that can carry over to the rest of your life. It doesn&rsquo;t have to be these things, though. If you enjoy running, for example, then do sprints, or check out Parkour. What matters is forcing you into the moment and, to a lesser extent, getting the endorphine rush that comes with a strenuous workout.</p>

<h2>Get Outside And Go For A Walk</h2>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t so much about fitness (the walk), but more about getting outside. Most people, and especially those with depression, are deficient in Vitamin D. <em>The</em> best way to get Vitamin D is from spending some time out in the sun, without sunscreen (Vitamin D synthesis is triggered by UV exposure, which is blocked by sunscreen). The walk is an added bonus to get the blood flowing, loosen stiff joints, and help build and maintain a base level of fitness, and just getting away from the computer helps your mind take a break and subconsciously mull over that problem you&rsquo;ve been dealing with all morning. I personally enjoy tossing on a Podcast and walking for about an hour at an easy pace (shout out to Shawn McCool and his Laravel.io podcast, which are pretty consistently about an hour). If you want a virtual walking buddy, feel free to <a href="http://runkeeper.com/user/gordondev">hit me up on RunKeeper</a> (great app to track your routes and distances, by the way).</p>

<h2>Take A Spa Day Once In A While</h2>

<p>Seriously, it seems really girly to have a spa day once in a while, but it&rsquo;s astounding how good it can be at relaxing you (and there are places that will give men massages and facials, too). Like the intense workout, it helps prompt you to be in the moment, and it feels extraordinarily good to get a nice massage (I&rsquo;m a fan of deep tissue massages, myself) and release that pent up tension in your shoulders and back.</p>

<p>If you <em>really</em> don&rsquo;t like the idea of a spa day (or can&rsquo;t afford it), do something similarly relaxing, even if it&rsquo;s just a hot bath or meditation. Being able to physically relax your body for a time can help relieve low-level psychological stress, which can, in turn, increase your motivation to get things done. Some type of &ldquo;me&rdquo; day also gives you something to look forward to, if you need something to get you through the day.</p>

<h2>Create A Todo List</h2>

<p>It feels good to me to check off an item on a list. At the very least, though, I&rsquo;ve found it helps get that list out of my head and off-load it from my memory, so that I can use those cognitive resources for <em>actually getting that shit done.</em> This has proven to be a <em>huge</em> benefit to my productivity &mdash; particularly for my side projects &mdash; as I find myself glancing at the list and going &ldquo;I want to work on that tonight.&rdquo; Even if I don&rsquo;t finish the task in question, I don&rsquo;t have to worry about keeping it on my mental list, because it&rsquo;s on a physical/digital one. It actually allows me to juggle the few dozen ideas and side projects I have bouncing around my head, without feeling overwhelmed by them (which is good, because they&rsquo;re all freakin' time-consuming as hell, and I can&rsquo;t generally just knock two or three out in an evening).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become a fan of <a href="http://www.any.do/">Any.do</a>, because I can set recurrances (like doing Yoga each day), or set some tasks to &ldquo;Someday,&rdquo; which keeps them separate from the stuff to do &ldquo;Today.&rdquo; I also love the integration it has with my Android phone, including a calendar app (it&rsquo;s got a slick interface).</p>

<p>I also enjoy <a href="https://workflowy.com/">Workflowy</a>, and used it for a short time as a Todo list, as well. It&rsquo;s become more of a shopping list for me when I do use it, but I know a few people who prefer it over other things for any kind of list making. There are many others to choose from, too, so it doesn&rsquo;t really matter <em>what</em> tool you use, as long as it works for you.</p>

<h2>Keep A Clean Working Area</h2>

<p>Clutter is often a trigger for stress. It can add cognitive overhead and lower your stress tolerance or threshold for getting overwhelmed. So, while it may not seem like it&rsquo;s adding stress or exacerbating depression symptoms, it might still be affecting you. Keep your work area (and, ideally, any area you spend a fair amount of time in) clutter free. In practice, this works best if you keep it clean, instead of trying to clean it while in a low state (though if it&rsquo;s mild enough, or if the clutter is light enough, cleaning it up might serve as a motivation booster).</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>Hopefully, one or more of these suggestions will help. I&rsquo;ve found, too, that a lot of these work best when you make a habit out of them. A single walk is pretty good, by itself, but making it a daily (or nearly so) habit helps keep your body increase its energy levels over time, giving you a higher base level of energy, which makes getting things done just a little bit easier. So, give one or two (or three) a shot for a couple of weeks and see how they work for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You're Not Alone]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/08/19/youre-not-alone/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T13:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2014/08/19/youre-not-alone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been torn over how open I should be with this, particularly in my professional life. My first instinct has been for it to be on a very need to know basis.</p>

<p>Then I met <a href="http://baugues.com/">Greg Baugues</a>.</p>

<p>Greg is a developer evangelist (devangelist) for <a href="http://www.twilio.com/">Twilio</a>, who speaks at conferences about his ADHD and Type II Bipolar, and he gets well-deserved standing ovations pretty much wherever he speaks. I still fight tearing up just thinking about <a href="http://userscape.com/laracon/2014/gregbaugues.html">the talk I attended at Laracon</a>, back in mid-May, where he even took his Bipolar medication on stage.</p>

<p>If you ever have the opportunity, attend this man’s talk. Even if you’ve seen the videos of it.</p>

<p>He’s the driving force behind this entry. Until now, I’ve kept my professional image away from my more personal parts. I’ve compartmentalized my identity, basically. Tech and business here, mental and physical health over there, homesteading over there (insert gestures to different directions here). But the truth is, my having Autism and Depression are part of what shapes me as a person and affects my professional life, whether I want them to or not. And just like I have started looking up to Greg as a role model for someone who has seen success with his ADHD and Bipolar out in the open, the others out there need more people to look up to, as well. We all need people to understand us and our differences, so that they can see us as strengths to be embraced, instead of liabilities to be feared. And, as Robin Williams’ death has shown so vividly, we need to be able to talk about these things openly and not be ashamed of them.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>I Am Autistic</h2>

<p>My official diagnosis is actually Asperger’s Syndrome, but as of the release of the DSM-V in May 2013, that got rolled into the “official” Autism name. It never really wasn’t part of the Autism Spectrum, but now it just goes by the name High Functioning Autism. Either way, it means that I can blend in with others most of the time, but still relate better to the little boy who freaks out at the crying baby, runs to a corner, and starts rocking back and forth.</p>

<p>In his talk, Greg brought up the “Hunter-Farmer hypothesis,” which is commonly used to explain the origin of ADHD. It’s an interesting theory that basically states that such differences in neurological functioning were not only beneficial, but arguably <em>essential</em> when we were hunter-gatherers, but that since we settled down and started farming, those differences started becoming maladaptive. Those with ADHD now would have been the hunters then, with laser focus under pressure, and bursts of high activity. They may have even been able to “fly under the radar” for generations as soldiers, which experience the same kind of peak and trough routine (or as Greg put it, “War has been described as long periods of boredom punctuated by moments of sheer terror.”), and it’s only very recently, when we’ve all been forced to sit still for hours on end from the time we’re five years old, that it’s become a problem, and since it started becoming a problem, it has exploded in our faces.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>There is a hypthesis that parallels ADHD-as-hunter, known as the <a href="http://www.epjournal.net/wp-content/uploads/EP09207238.pdf">Solitary Forager Hypthesis</a>. In it, Jared Reser explores the idea that some of the common symptoms of Autism &mdash; repetition, rote memorization, obsession over things modern society deems trivial &mdash; may have been highly beneficial traits in hunter-gatherer times. Additionally, the Autistic’s ability to work alone and not be wholly dependent on social groups may have been advantageous, especially in tribes that lived in places where foraging took the individuals far and away from each other for great lengths of time. Like those with ADHD were probably able to find their niches until very recently, I think so did Autistics, in the form of artisans, scholars, and monks &mdash; who spent their entire lives replicating things, doing the same thing over and over, and meticulously honing their craft in a near-obsessive way, with some going so far as to not talk to others and taking a vow of silence.</p>

<p>Reser concludes with this, which I think is a phenomenal philosophy for not just Autism, but ADHD and several other neuro-atypical states:</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<h2>I Also Have Depression</h2>

<p>The outpouring of awareness support for mental illness in the wake of Robin Williams' death has sparked a rise, especially in the developer community, of efforts to end the stigma around mental illness, so that those with them don’t feel ashamed to seek help. I am no exception for either giving or needing to receive that support, and I hope this marks a more permanent rise in such movements than what past losses have seen.</p>

<p>I was diagnosed with Depressive Disorder Not Otherwise Specified (DD-NOS) after a late-term miscarriage that, for all intents and purposes, shattered every fiber of my being. That event not only turned me into a vastly different (and unfortunately, more fragile) person, but it exacerbated what was already there.</p>

<p>The truth of the matter is that I’ve suffered from Depression to one degree or another for about as long as I can remember. Whether it was slowly ingrained into me by a life surrounded by abusive people, both peers and those in positions of authority, or if it was there first and just painted a target on my back for those people, I don’t know. Frankly, it doesn’t matter anymore.</p>

<p>Even when I was younger, the thought of suicide had crossed my mind on more than one occasion, and in recent years, such thoughts have increased in frequency, though I’ve always been too selfless to actually go through with it, because I don’t want to upset my family, and don’t want to put the stress of things like a funeral and being a single father on my husband. It’s not that I think suicide is a “selfish” act &mdash; I don’t believe it is &mdash; but rather that I’m not a very selfish or self-serving person by nature. I’m driven to please others or feel “needed” or “useful.” Something like suicide is the polar opposite to that, and, therefore, takes a considerable amount of effort just to do it. It probably also helps that I end up over-thinking and, in a sense, “over-engineering” my way out of actually going through with it.</p>

<p>I mention the miscarriage, because that’s really also something else that needs to be talked about more. Did you know that the miscarriage rate is upwards of 50% of all pregnancies when chemical pregnancies and other very early miscarriages are taken into account? I didn’t know that, either, until 2006. Even excluding those, the miscarriage rate for Western society is still about 20%. In other words, for every 5 women you know, one of them will have miscarried a known pregnancy. Late term miscarriages &mdash; any that happen betmaween 12 and 24 weeks &mdash; have a rate of 1 in 100, and stillbirths &mdash; after 24 weeks &mdash; have a rate of 1 in 160. This means that odds are very good that you’ve met at least one woman who has lost a pregnancy. And yet, how many of us know the people that have suffered through this? This is why we need to talk more about it, especially since late term miscarriages and stillbirths are particularly devastating.</p>

<p>At that point, you’ve bonded with your unborn child. You’ve probably already had a baby shower. The nursery’s almost done, you’re part way through those birthing classes. You’ve seen the “big” ultrasound. And then, one day, everything grinds to a screeching, horrific, agonizing halt.</p>

<p>But it doesn’t end there, and this is one of those things that really no one talks about. For most sudden traumatic events, the actual event is over relatively quickly, and once it’s done, you can focus on healing, possibly with the help of painkillers. It doesn’t work that way for a woman that experiences a late-term loss, because the body still goes through the postnatal motions <em>as though nothing bad has happened.</em> This includes lactating. The worst pain in the world &mdash; producing milk for an infant that isn’t there &mdash; there are no painkillers for that two weeks of hell.</p>

<p>Yes, this was very much my breaking point, and the best image I have for it is quite literally a glass item dropping and shattering into a few million pieces. It’s a shame <em>Eragon</em> the movie didn’t hold true to the books, or the shattering of the Star Sapphire at the Battle of Farthen Dur would have been a perfect image for those who haven’t gone through such a loss (as it stands, it’s still a perfect metaphor). Unfortunately, unlike the dwarves in <em>Eragon</em>, we don’t have dragon magic to restore us to our former glory, even if we and our fleet of people dedicated to piecing us back together could manage to do so.</p>

<p>Like <a href="https://medium.com/@kayladnls/youre-not-alone-f210b82893cb">a good friend of mine, Kayla,</a> related, there are a number of times where I’ve sat alone and cried, or cried myself to sleep. Sometimes, there may be a trigger &mdash; not a reason, per se, but rather, something that starts the chain reaction. Maybe it’s a bad day at work, a fight with my husband, or my mind replaying real or imagined horrors. Other times, there’s no known reason at all, just the nothingness itself weighing down on me.</p>

<h2>I’m Not Alone</h2>

<p><a href="http://archive.wired.com/wired/archive/9.12/aspergers_pr.html">Wired Magazine</a> nailed it way back in 2004: the stereotypical “geek” is more likely to be on the Autism Spectrum (and therefore have kids who are also on the Spectrum). And it’s true, computers and electronics, and the professional fields that revolve around them, attract people with varying levels of Autism. I suspect that it largely has to do with the fact that technology itself (and math in general) is based on clear-cut rules and standards, and those rules and standards usually have a reason behind them. There may be a hundred ways to solve a problem, but all of those ways still require laying out a set of rules to achieve an end. Technology <em>makes sense</em> in a world that is otherwise run by arbitrary nonsense to us. So, if you work in, or in any way interact with people who work in, technology, odds are, you’ve met someone with Autism, even if you didn’t realize it.</p>

<p>Even if you aren’t involved at all with anything technology-related, with the Autism diagnostic rate somewhere between 1 in 50 and 1 in 68 (depending on who you ask), odds are, you’ve met someone with Autism. And since not everyone with Autism gravitates toward technology, it may even be that new artist you saw at your local gallery, or the odd neighbor kid.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<h2>What Does It All Mean?</h2>

<p>For me, it means I’ve got a witty, no-holds-barred, sarcastic, confident woman trapped inside a fearful, anxiety-filled body and brain. I can’t count the number of times I’ve imagined a conversation &mdash; any conversation &mdash; where I’d be able to make some kind of witty response, or even just stand up for myself without shutting down, and actually succeed at doing so.</p>

<p>I’ve had a running theory that Autism is largely and input/output disorder &mdash; the common threads in nearly all Autistics is difficulty processing input (sensory overload, slow auditory processing, etc), and difficulty turning it into output (difficulty with spoken conversation, not showing emotion, etc). As such, there are a number of myths that have formed, as researchers and doctors try to make sense of Autism and help people with it. I’ll go into detail another time, as there’s a lot to be said on the matter, but I’ll touch on some of the things in a moment.</p>

<p>My personal history with both Autism and Depression have made me a very self-aware kind of person. This is very much a double-edge sword, because I can see where failure points are, but don’t always have the knowledge or means of <em>correcting</em> said failure points. In other words, I can see <em>that</em> something is failing (usually communication), but I can’t figure out <em>why</em> or what to do about it or even to mitigate the resulting issues. This occasionally leads to a negative feedback loop, where the Depression starts to take over in the form of despair for being able to get things right.</p>

<h3>Okay, But What Does It <em>Mean</em>?</h3>

<p>Waxing philosophical about the ups and downs of both matters is a great pass time, but what does it mean for those around me, in day-to-day interactions?</p>

<p>Well, first, let me address some misconceptions of primarily Autism, and to a lesser extent, Depression:</p>

<ul>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I am violent, prone to violence, or will become a serial killer (or any other form of murderer).</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I am mentally disabled.</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I lack empathy or have no feelings, though I may feel and express them differently from other people.</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that my Autism in need of a “cure,” or that I otherwise need “fixed.” My Depression may be a mental illness, but my Autism is not, and there is a difference.</li>
<li>It <strong>does not</strong> mean that I’m constantly under suicide watch or that I’d do something drastic just because someone said something I didn’t like.</li>
<li><p>If I happen to be on antidepressants at the time, it <strong>does not</strong> mean that I have to be happy all the time, or that the medication is not working if I show even the slightest hint of a negative emotion.</p></li>
<li><p>It <strong>does</strong> mean that I communicate better through asynchronous means (writing, as opposed to speaking), for a multitude of reasons.</p></li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that sometimes I will get overstressed and need to remove myself from the situation, and that when that happens, I need enough respect and compassion from others to give me some space and time.</li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that I do better knowing things ahead of time, such as changes in schedules or meeting agendas (especially when said meeting is prone to be emotionally charged or critical of me/my work).</li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that, particularly when it comes to social infractions, I genuinely may not know what has upset someone, and telling me “you’re smart, you can figure it out,” does not help me.</li>
<li>It <strong>does</strong> mean that I will <em>always</em> prioritize the things that help me <em>above all else</em>. This includes proper diet and exercise, and the means and time to achieve those. This also means that I am <em>very protective</em> of my work-life balance, and will strive to ensure that I’m not working more than I can handle. My ability to stop working at a reasonable hour so that I can participate in that day’s workout and cook my dinner as opposed to ordering pizza and soda is what allows me to be productive each day and keep working on the things that make my employer money. No job is worth my well-being, especially since sacrificing the latter will inevitably sacrifice the former.</li>
</ul>


<h2>What Can We Do?</h2>

<h3>Recognize That Not Everyone Who Is Sick Looks So</h3>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Twerkerella/status/501230591615201281/photo/1">This image illustrates the problem quite well</a>, as does <a href="http://www.butyoudontlooksick.com/wpress/articles/written-by-christine/the-spoon-theory/">this story</a>, for those more inclined for words.</p>

<p>If you do not suffer from an invisible illness, recognize that just because you can’t <em>see</em> the symptoms, it doesn’t mean they’re not there. They are very much there, very much real, and those of us with them spend every waking moment doing what we can to keep it from consuming us and our lives. For some of us, the very act of getting out of bed is little short of a miracle. What you see is generally an act or part of a plan to get through the day and meet such needs as earning money.</p>

<p>We’re not being lazy or making excuses when we say we can’t do something. Do you say that a paraplegic is just being lazy by not walking, or a blind person just isn’t trying hard enough at seeing? No? The same applies to mental illness. A person suffering from Depression can’t just “try harder” at being happy. It doesn’t work that way.</p>

<h3>Provide Reasonable Work Hours and Conditions</h3>

<p>If you’re an employer, especially in the tech industry, remember that not everyone is a healthy, single, 20-something who has no life outside of working for you, and that <em>this is not a bad thing.</em> Different people bring different experiences and knowledge to the table, providing valuable input.</p>

<p>Instead of viewing these things as liabilities, view them as assets to be cultivated and nurtured. Really, all people should be treated this way, as no one should have to work ungodly numbers of hours every day. That’s a sure path to destruction of even the healthiest of individuals, though it may take longer.</p>

<p>For those with mental illnesses, it’s better to be able to work shorter hours, which keeps us from long-term destruction, than to run us ragged and destroy us in a few months or, at best, a couple of years. It’s been shown that <em>everyone</em> &mdash; with or without any kind of chronic illness &mdash; does better on shorter hours and that long hours are <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2013/07/09/news/economy/shorter-work-week/">at best useless and at worst counterproductive</a>. There’s a reason labor laws are supposed to limit workers to 40 hours a week (“exempt” status notwithstanding), and those reasons don’t just apply to the blue collar workers for whom such laws are actually enforced.</p>

<h3>Talk</h3>

<p>For those of us with mental illnesses, we can start by talking about it. There are a couple of hashtags floating around Twitter. The main one is <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23endthestigma&amp;src=tyah">#EndTheStigma</a>, which includes not just mental health, but other stigmatized things as well. There’s also a new one rising up, called <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23hackthestigma&amp;src=typd">#HackTheStigma</a>, that was originally created due to not wanting to be associated with the “End The Stigma” campaigns used by some companies.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not ready to talk openly, you can reach out to me or any of the others in the community that have opened their inboxes and/or phones.</p>

<p>We’re here. You’re not alone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project: Octopress Theme Toytown]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/25/project-octopress-theme-toytown/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-25T09:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2013/01/25/project-octopress-theme-toytown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of yet another redesign and blog migration, I needed to create a theme that wasn&rsquo;t so stock. I migrated my site to <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, a blogging platform that runs on GitHub&rsquo;s <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> static site generator. It&rsquo;s a great platform, as anyone who follows my Twitter or Google+ accounts is aware, but the vast majority of sites that run on Octopress use the default theme, or some slight variation thereof. As good and nice as the default theme is, it&rsquo;s become very generic. I needed something different.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why &ldquo;Toytown&rdquo;?</h2>

<p>The entire theme is based around the image in the background. That image is actually one of the views I get to see in the mornings and evenings when I go to and leave from work.</p>

<p>You see, my office is located in one of the biggest shopping districts in the city, and it&rsquo;s pretty unique in that it&rsquo;s built as a blend between an indoor shopping mall and street-facing shops. Every year for the holidays (and evidently, well into the new year, for whatever reason), they string up lights on every building. It always reminds me of a gingerbread town, because of the way the lights are done &ndash; it&rsquo;s &ldquo;warm&rdquo; white rope lights lined along the corners and some other accent lines, much the same way you&rsquo;d have the frosting on a gingerbread building. They also have a couple of giant Christmas trees in the main open areas to the north and south of the main &ldquo;mall&rdquo; area. I have no doubt that, if viewed from above, in, say, a helicopter, it would look more like something you&rsquo;d find in a toy or model train store than an actual shopping center.</p>

<h2>The Keystone of the Theme</h2>

<p>Combine the natural &ldquo;toy-like&rdquo; aspect of the area this time of year, with the view from a few dozen feet above ground level, and a little manipulation in Gimp to create a <a href="http://www.inspiration.scottphotographics.com/amazing-miniature-tilt-shift-photography/">tilt-shift miniature effect</a>, and you end up with a fun background that looks more like a model than a real place.</p>

<p>The first image I had of it wasn&rsquo;t as high quality as I&rsquo;d like, due to having taken it with my smartphone, especially at the scale needed to adequately make it a background for a website. So, as much as I loved the image itself (because it was late enough in the morning to be &ldquo;daytime&rdquo;, but you could still see the lights on the buildings), I decided to go out and take more pictures, this time with an actual camera. (Note: as of 1/25/13, the &ldquo;first image&rdquo; is still the one used. I don&rsquo;t have access to an SD card reader at the moment, so I can&rsquo;t get the pictures off of my camera.)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also this image that I derived the color theme from, with the aid of the wonderfully useful <a href="http://colorschemedesigner.com">Color Scheme Designer</a>. The entire theme actually consists of just three base colors, with which I played with shades, hues, and opacity to achieve the desired effects.</p>

<p>Ah, the joys of working in the digital realm.</p>

<h2>Layout</h2>

<p>Since it&rsquo;s largely a blog these days (I still have my &ldquo;About&rdquo; page, which has the online version of my resume and will eventually sport the download options, as well, but the main focal point is the blog), I decided to stick with the two-column theme, allowing for various supplementary things, such as recent or related posts, tag clouds, and so forth.</p>

<p>Additionally, I&rsquo;ve made the site responsive. Anything above a 920px wide screen (or its rought equivalent, as it also responds to text size; more on that later), will have a single-column experience, with the extra goodies at the bottom. As the viewport gets smaller, some items will even shift their layout entirely, to accommodate the typical touch input of what are typically smaller screens. I also drop out the background image entirely (or rather, I don&rsquo;t add it in until larger sizes), to help keep bandwidth lower on devices that are more likely to be on a connection where download size is important.</p>

<h2>320 and Up? Kind of.</h2>

<p>One of the big new paradigms in web development is what&rsquo;s known as &ldquo;mobile first&rdquo; development. Among the large frameworks and bootstrapping tools is <a href="http://www.stuffandnonsense.co.uk/blog/about/this_is_the_new_320_and_up">320 and Up</a>, which starts its <abbr title="Cascading Style Sheets">CSS</abbr> media query &ldquo;breakpoints&rdquo; with 320px wide (the most narrow viewport size that most modern smartphones use) and work up from there.
Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}
Until 1px no longer equals 1px.</p>

<p>This is exactly what we&rsquo;re seeing with the new high-density (&ldquo;retina&rdquo;) displays, which have upwards of two or more times the number of Dots Per Inch as a 96<abbr title="Dots Per Inch">DPI</abbr> screen. To compound matters, these new devices don&rsquo;t have the same pixel densities. In fact, their densities are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_displays_by_pixel_density#Devices_by_manufacturers">all over the map</a>. 151, 132, 202, etc. Even if you go off of the &ldquo;CSS pixel ratio&rdquo;, you still have 1, 1.325, 1.5, 2, and who-knows-what else in the future (and you <em>know</em> not all of the real pixel densities match well to the &ldquo;CSS pixel ratio&rdquo;).</p>

<p>Oh yeah, and, in part because of the above, these devices basically lie about their resolutions. The &ldquo;Retina&rdquo; iPhones report their resolutions as half of what they actually are. Additionally, some devices will increase their font size, but report a resolution that looks like a desktop.</p>

<p>So what to do? <a href="http://blog.cloudfour.com/the-ems-have-it-proportional-media-queries-ftw/">How about not use pixel-based media queries to begin with?</a> This has two added bonuses &ndash; you no longer have to worry about CSS pixel to device pixel differences, and you can adjust based on zoom level.</p>

<p>Go ahead, zoom in on the site. Isn&rsquo;t that cool?</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s one of the first projects I&rsquo;ve actually done using the &ldquo;mobile-first&rdquo; paradigm, as well as using EMs, so it could probably use some polish, but it was fun to learn, and it even looks good on my Android devices.</p>

<h2>Other Technologies</h2>

<h3>HTML5 and CSS</h3>

<p>Since it&rsquo;s an Octopress theme, it makes heavy use of HTML5, <a href="http://sass-lang.com">Sass</a>, and <a href="http://compass-style.org/">Compass</a>. I didn&rsquo;t do much with the HTML (I didn&rsquo;t need to), but I rewrote the CSS to better fit my programming style and make it simpler to do a simple color scheme change, without having to guess at the variable names.</p>

<p>There is also a fair amount of CSS3 thrown into the mix, with a couple of transitions (namely, mouseover effects for the links), some rounded corners, and alpha-transparent backgrounds.</p>

<h3>Ruby and YAML</h3>

<p>Most of this section doesn&rsquo;t really relate to the theme itself, but since building the theme was part of the project of redoing my site, I&rsquo;m just going to include this, as well. The theme itself really only needs the HTML and CSS related stuff.</p>

<p>Since GitHub is a Ruby shop, it&rsquo;s only natural that Jekyll and, by extension, Octopress are Ruby based. I didn&rsquo;t delve a whole lot into the Ruby code, but I did use it a little to customize a couple of plugins I found (incidentally, before I found better ones), and to add a little template logic into the header section, to display things like a link to GitHub, or a &ldquo;Highlights&rdquo; page (in my case, I used the &ldquo;Highlights&rdquo; page to list all entries under the &ldquo;projects&rdquo; category). I also added a couple entries to the Gemfile to add the GSL and Classifier gems to the Bundler install script, so that I could make use of the &ldquo;related posts&rdquo; capabilities of Jekyll.</p>

<p>The configuration is all done through YAML files, which, of course, requires editing them so that things work as I want them to. This includes defining a separate set of sidebar widgets for the individual post view page vs the list view page, adding my own configuration options for the theme, and activating the &ldquo;related posts&rdquo; plugin. I also added an abbreviations plugin, which contains a list of known abbreviations and wraps any it finds in posts or pages in <code>&lt;abbr&gt;</code> tags. I&rsquo;ve added significantly to this list, so that it covers more abbreviations.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/octopress-theme-toytown">The theme is up on GitHub</a>, so feel free to fork it and play around with it. I made it largely for personal use, so I have next to no documentation for it, but I&rsquo;ve tried to make it simple enough that it should be easy to modify. It&rsquo;s also probably going to be an evolving project, as I find things I don&rsquo;t like or are broken entirely. All in all, it&rsquo;s been a fun project so far, though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun with Python!]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/05/04/fun-with-python/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2012/05/04/fun-with-python</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I'm terrible about coming up with projects to do to learn a new language. As such, I generally pick them up as jobs require them. This makes it difficult to find a good reason to pick up a new language for me. So, when I made the decision earlier this week to learn Python, I decided to go a slightly different route - Gedit plugin development!</p> <!-- more --><p>So, I picked a plugin from the Gnome Gedit plugin wishlist and was going to start with it. At the time, I was using Gedit for some development (because it allowed me to edit on the remote server that I need to use for a project), but I felt it was lacking in some things that I thought would be useful (after already loading it up with plugins). That actually lead me to seeing if something was already out there. Then I remembered the <a href="https://github.com/gmate/gmate">Gmate project</a>.</p> <p>Gmate has some great plugins, but Gnome 3 is out now, and with it, Gedit 3, and a new Gedit API. This means that all the old plugins need updated to work with Gedit 3. For some reason, not all of the plugins in the Gmate package have been updated yet, so I decided against writing a new plugin from scratch and work on porting the Gmate stuff.</p> <p>And that's what I did. I've so far successfully ported Gemini, a basic bracket-completion plugin, and am currently working on Find In Files. For those interested, my fork can be found <a href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/gmate">here, on Github</a>.</p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Templates for Munin]]></title>
    <link href="http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/04/18/jeremy-clarke-made-nice-sleek/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ShaunaGordon.com/blog/2011/04/18/jeremy-clarke-made-nice-sleek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Jeremy Clarke made a nice, sleek theme/template set for Munin (see his <a href="http://simianuprising.com/2011/02/19/raven-my-custom-theme-templates-for-munin/" target="_blank">original post</a> about it). Since, like him, I hate the default theme (it's ugly, and done in 90s style table layout), I wanted to change it, but I currently don't have the time to write my own theme (not that there's much documentation on the topic, despite how awesome Munin actually is). Jeremy's seems to be the only one on the entire Internet aside from the default and default-alt themes, and he did a great job with what he had. However, I had some issues getting it working on the version I'm running (1.4.4). It was mainly just missing files (kinda-sorta-not really his fault, Munin should probably just ignore things like missing images and allow the page to break, instead of halting copying the files to the html directory).</p><p>Anywho, so I grabbed the copy by Kim (in the comments), who was kind enough to update the theme for 1.4.* (it was originally for 1.3.*), but her copy didn't have the required files, either. So, I got it working in my test environment and then updated the template folder with the necessary files. I'm posting it here for easy downloading.</p><p><a title="Raven theme GitHub project" href="https://github.com/ShaunaGordon/raven-munin-theme">Download Raven Munin theme.</a></p></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
